<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anti-christ in man, or, A discovery of the great whore that sits upon many waters wherein is declared what that whore or inward mystery is, together with the destruction thereof, by the powerfull appearing of Christ in us / by Joseph Salmon ...</title>
            <author>Salmon, Joseph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60500</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S413</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39105</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18213175</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18213175</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107173</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60500)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107173)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1129:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anti-christ in man, or, A discovery of the great whore that sits upon many waters wherein is declared what that whore or inward mystery is, together with the destruction thereof, by the powerfull appearing of Christ in us / by Joseph Salmon ...</title>
                  <author>Salmon, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 73 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation XVII, 5 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Antichrist.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107173:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107173:1"/>
            <p>ANTI-CHRIST in Man: OR A diſcovery of the <hi>Great WHORE</hi> that ſits upon many Waters, Wherein is declared what that <hi>Whore</hi> or inward <hi>Myſtery</hi> is; together with the deſtruction thereof, by the powerfull appearing of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in us.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOSEPH SALMON,</hi> a Member of the <hi>ARMY.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 18.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And he cryed mightily with a ſtrong voice ſaying, Babylon is fallen, is fallen, and is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the habitation of devils, and a cage of every unclean and hatefull bird.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ver. 20.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>Rejoyce over her, thou heaven, and yee ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtles, and Prophets, for God hath avenged you on her.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Sign of the Black ſpread <hi>Eagle</hi> at the weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:107173:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107173:2"/>
            <head>To all thoſe who deſire to be acquainted with the Myſtery of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and eſpecially to thoſe my beloved friends and Brethren in the Lord, with whom I have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly walked in outward formall Communion, both in City and Country.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y dear friends, whoſe I am in the bowels of unfained love; conſidering with my ſelfe, that there is nothing more requiſite to be known, then theſe two great myſteries, the myſtery of godlineſs, and the myſtery of iniquity; and likewiſe pondering how much all fleſh is oppoſite to the diſcovery of theſe two myſteries; I have preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to dictate my thoughts unto you in this ſmall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, wherein I have briefly and infirmely diſcovered
<pb facs="tcp:107173:3"/>unto you, what the Lord hath manifeſted unto me of the ſpirit of Antichriſt, that is in all of us: It may be that I may be ſuppoſed, by many of you, in this little volume, to endeavour the ſubvertion and overture of that forme and diſcipline that you for the preſent walk in; but I aſſure you from the truth of my heart, that I intend no ſuch thing; but ſhall rather incourage any of you to continue in that diſpenſation, where the Tord doth manifeſt himſelf to you in the ſame: only this know dear friends, that the Lord hath his movings towards his people, to ſome he ſhewes himſelf more clearly; to ſeme more obſcurely; to ſome he makes the fleſh of Chriſt comfortable, and joyfull; that is, the diſcovery of himſelfe in flleſhly diſpenſations; to others he cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifies his own fleſh (as I may ſo ſay) that is, dyes, departs, goes away in the fleſh, or fleſhly formes and diſpenſations; and this is my condition for the preſent; I were a wretch if I ſhould deny the appearances of God to me in that way you now for the preſent ſtand in; but now it hath pleaſed God to move out of theſe things to me, I now ſee, that all the knowledge of Chriſt that they could ſet out to me, was but o knowledge of him after the fleſh; in a word, I ſee that Chriſt hath cruciſied himſelfe to me, in all theſe things in which before I enjoyed his fleſhly preſence; inſomuch that I now waite with the Diſciples, where Jeſus hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed me, even at the gates of wiſdomes houſe, and at the poſts of wiſdomes doors, for the return of the
<pb facs="tcp:107173:3"/>Spirit; for I believe this departed Jeſus will come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, but it ſhall he in Spirit; not in fleſh; and will make himſelf to be that ſubſtance to me really, which I catched at in the ſhadow typecally; and this, through mercy, I doe in ſome meaſure enjoy, and though in much imperfection, yet ſo ſweetly, that henceforth I deſire to know Chriſt after the fleſh no longer.</p>
            <p>Now as concerning this Treatiſe it ſelf, I deſire you to look upon it as comming from a Child in the underſtanding of the divine things of God, and if you ſuppoſe your ſelves to have come to more maturity in divinity then my ſelfe, and that you think that you can ſpeak in more glory then I have done, I hope you will be ſo muh the more engaged to paſſe a charitable cenſure upon the ſtammerings of my Infancy: If any of you ſhall notwithſtanding teſtifie any rigedneſſe of ſpirit againſt me in this particutar; herein I joy and rejoyce, that the Lord in his time will bring you to live ſo in the light of that Sunne, as that you ſhall ſee all your now preſent light, to be darkneſſe, and your forme to be fleſh, and then you will not be bitter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any poore Saint, that deſires to enjoy God in a more high diſpenſation then your ſelves; in the meane time, I deſire your prayers to the Lord for me, and I ſhall for ever commit you into his hands, who I hope ere long will dye to you in all theſe outward things, as he hath to me, and by his riſing and ſecond comming in you, will ſo manifeſt himſelf to you, that you ſhall ſee
<pb facs="tcp:107173:4"/>him to be the ſpirituall water, bread and wine, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out and beyond all theſe types, and ſhadowes; which is the dayly prayer of him who ſtill profeſſeth himſelf to be your brother, by that one Baptiſme of that one ſpirit, into that one body; and for ever remain yours til death.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joſeph Salmon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107173:4"/>
            <head>ANTICHRIST in Man: OR The diſcovery of the great <hi>WHORE</hi> that ſits upoh many waters.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here hath been much contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercy about the finding out of this great <hi>Whore;</hi> that ſpirit of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> which God ſhall judge, and whom Chriſt ſhall deſtroy, <hi>by the breath of his mouth, and the brightneſs of his comming:</hi> and in this eager perſuit of her, to find her out in her ſcarlet colours, riding upon the Beaſt; ſome men have atained to glimmerings, ſome to a more perfect diſcovery of her; ſome there are that affirme this great <hi>Whore</hi> to be the <hi>Pope;</hi> ſome the <hi>Presbyter,</hi> ſome the <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> now theſe men have ſeen the <hi>Whore</hi> but in a fleſhly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107173:5"/>they take the fruite for the tree, the ſtreame for the fountain; in a word, they have ſeen her outſide, but not her inſide; they know her in the Hiſtory, but not in the Miſtery; for <hi>upon her Fore-head is written, MISTERY, BA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BYLON, THE GREAT, &amp;c. Rev.</hi> 17.5.</p>
            <p>Know therefore O man, whomſoever thou art! that judgeſt the whore by theſe carnall conceptions of her, that thou art far deceived by her, in her fleſhly appearances to thee:</p>
            <p>Thus while the ſons of men ſeeke to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold this Strumpet in her proper ſphere and <hi>center,</hi> they deceive themſelves, by looking too fleſhly and carnally upon her: know firſt then O man! that this great <hi>whore</hi> is in thee, whil'ſt thou ſeekeſt to behold her without thee, whil'ſt thou beholdeſt her in other men, ſhee is in the mean time acting in a <hi>Myſtery</hi> in thee: whileſt thou deſpiſeſt the appearance of her in other men, ſhee hath by guile caught thee, and by her <hi>Myſterious workings</hi> inſnared thee; and hath ſtolen thy heart from <hi>God</hi> and good neſs, ſhe imbraceth the in her armes; ſhe kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thee with her mouth; ſhe deceiveth thee by her flatteries, whileſt thou thinkeſt thou haſt nothing to doe with her; ſhee is in thy boſome, whileſt thou thinkeſt ſhee is far diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant from thee; and this is done in a miſtery and thou ſeeſt it not.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:107173:5"/>
            <p>Now then looking upon this <hi>Whore ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,</hi> not carnally; <hi>in us,</hi> and not out of us; <hi>in the Myſtery,</hi> and not in the hiſtery: once more let us make inquiſition after her, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to finde her out in all her ſubtil and cloſe corners. For thy better attaining to the diſcovery of her conſider;</p>
            <p>Firſt, what this great <hi>Whore</hi> is.</p>
            <p>Secondly, how ſhee works, and what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences ſhee deludes the ſoule by.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, how a ſoule comes to attain a ſight of her.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, and laſtly, how and when, ſhee ſhall bee deſtroyed: and thus wee may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to a ſight of <hi>Babylon, with her Riſe, and her down-fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt what is the Whore?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Whore,</hi> this <hi>Babylon,</hi> this <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> Is thy fleſhly wiſdome; that ſpirituall <hi>Serpent</hi> thou art deceived by, &amp; commiteſt fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with all, is the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of the fleſh, the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Policy of the creature.</p>
            <p>This was that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> that appeared in, and to our firſt Parents, and that which they harlotryed with, from the Lord: God He created <hi>Adam</hi> blind and naked, to this end, that <hi>Adam</hi> might not ſee, but God for him; nor <hi>Adam</hi> might not know, but what God knew in him, and for him; and ſo this <hi>Adam,</hi> though
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107173:6"/>blind and naked, yet cloathed with ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Robes, as were altogether inconſiſtant to fleſhly <hi>Adam;</hi> ſo here was God All, the Creature Nothing.</p>
            <p>But now comes the <hi>Serpent,</hi> which is, the ſubtileſt beaſt in mans worldly heart; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Selfe,</hi> and <hi>Fleſh;</hi> and that diſpences its wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome into the heart of the Creatures, and that bids them <hi>eat,</hi> for then their <hi>eyes</hi> ſhould be opened, and they ſhould be as Gods, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good and evill. Now man deſiring (by the report of fleſhly-wiſdome) to have his eyes opened, and to be as God, and to bee no more a ſubject, but a King; no longer govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but a governour; runs away from God, departs from his firſt Lover, and commits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery with his own fleſhly wiſdom: And as <hi>Adam,</hi> in the Hiſtory; ſo all in the Miſtery, commit dayly fornication with the <hi>Whore</hi> our fleſhly <hi>wiſdime;</hi> by cating of the forbidden Tree; for this forbidden Tree, is in us, and we taſt of it continually; and howerly ſuffer death for the ſame:</p>
            <p>This <hi>Garden of Eden,</hi> in the Miſtery, O man! is in thee; in whom God hath placed the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of him ſelf, &amp; hath brought forth the budings of his glory; and any of theſe thou mayeſt <hi>Eate;</hi> but there is a Tree in the mideſt of this Gard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of which thou mayeſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107173:6"/>not eate; which is thy heart, O man! this muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e reſerved wholy to the Lord; this God cals for, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.28. <hi>my ſon give mee thy heart:</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, thou muſt aſcribe nothing to thy ſelf; but give over al man in to my hands, and willing to be no more, then I will bee in thee; and to know no more then I ſhall know for thee; this is, that <hi>forbidden Tree</hi> that God would not have us eate of: but whole man, with his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Reaſon, Judgement, Affections, Will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Underſtanding, muſt be given to the <hi>Lord:</hi> but now comes this Serpent our ſubtil fleſhly wiſdome, in us; and that thinks much to let God be all, do all and have the glory of all: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut it would faine ſee with its own eyes, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee a God unto its ſelf; ſo it forſakes all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt of the Trees, which God hath given it to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate of; namely, the manifeſtation of God in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſoul; and takes of its owne fruite, &amp; eats <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f that feaſt that fleſh hath provided; and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orſakes the <hi>fountain, and runs to the broken Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ernes; Jer.</hi> 2.13. and thus our eyes comes to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee opened; and wee ſee no longer light, in Gods light; but with the eye of ſelf and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, <hi>ſaying to a ſtock, thou art my Father, and to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one, thou haſt brought me forth; Jer.</hi> 2.27. that is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tributing nothing to God, but all to fleſhly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſdome; with which wee have Adulterated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Harlotrized from the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:107173:7"/>
            <p>Thus O man! thou ſeeſt what that <hi>grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Whore is,</hi> and where ſhee lyeth; even in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt cloſets of thy ſoule. Now that thou mayeſt bee farther convinced, that this wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the fleſh, is <hi>the Antichriſt, the grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Whore:</hi> do but firſt conſider the <hi>Names,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly the <hi>Nature</hi> of her.</p>
            <p>Eirſt, her Names in Scripture are divers, a firſt, ſhe is called <hi>Anti-chriſt,</hi> which is as much as to ſay, <hi>againſt Chriſt:</hi> Now man as a creature is not againſt Chriſt; but the wiſdome of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fleſh in man, this is againſt Chriſt, and ſo, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the <hi>great Wore,</hi> or <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, She is called <hi>Babylon,</hi> in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.5. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.2. which is as muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as to ſay, <hi>confuſion,</hi> now all confuſion that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wrought either in <hi>Pope, Presbyter,</hi> or any othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> particular State, is by the wiſdome of the fleſh therefore this is that <hi>great Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, She is called that wicked one, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 8. Now all the actuall wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that proceeds from the ſons of me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> flowes from that originall within, even th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>wiſdome</hi> of the <hi>fleſh;</hi> therefore the wiſdome o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>fleſh,</hi> is that great wicked one, which is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, She is called the <hi>Mother of Harlo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd abominations of the earth, Rev.</hi> 17.5. No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what's the <hi>Mother of Harlots,</hi> ſurely this canno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:107173:7"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> either the <hi>Pope,</hi> or any other particular <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tate; for if the <hi>Pope</hi> be the <hi>Mother</hi> of <hi>Harlots,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en I demand who, or what, is the <hi>Mother</hi> of is <hi>Harlotry?</hi> Then what, or who, is the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er</hi> of <hi>Harlots?</hi> Why ſhe is in us all in a <hi>myſtery;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is the wiſdome of the <hi>fleſh</hi> in man, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Mother</hi> of all the abomination which is ommitted againſt the Lord.</p>
            <p>This is that <hi>Aanti-chriſt;</hi> this is <hi>Babylon;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere is the <hi>wicked one;</hi> this is the <hi>Matron</hi> of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iquity; out of the womb of fleſhly <hi>wiſdome</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roceeds all that actuall tranſgreſſion that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ommitted againſt the <hi>Lord:</hi> All outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earances of ſins, are but the <hi>Baſtards</hi> of this <hi>Whore,</hi> the <hi>children</hi> of this <hi>ſtrange Woman,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Brats</hi> of this great <hi>Adultereſs;</hi> and happy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea, thrice bleſſed ſhall that man be called, who ſhall take and daſh theſe <hi>children</hi> of the <hi>Whore againſt the ſtones;</hi> This man is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall come in power and great glory in a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and deſtroy, and daſh in peeces the conceptions, bringings forth, and appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>fleſhly wiſdome</hi> in us: as we ſhall ſhew more at large hereafter.</p>
            <p>Thus we have endeavoured to diſcover the <hi>whore</hi> what ſhee is by her <hi>Names</hi> given her in Scripture; whereby thou mayeſt underſtand, that the <hi>Whore</hi> doth not conſiſt of any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward State or fleſhly appearances to thee: but
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107173:8"/>upon her <hi>Fore-head;</hi> which is her moſt op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and palpable workings, there is written <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That this great <hi>Whore</hi> may yet mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fully appeare to be the wiſdome of the fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in thee, doe but conſider the nature of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Whore</hi> in brief, and ſo we ſhall have done wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the firſt quaere, Namely, <hi>What the Whore is?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Nature</hi> of this <hi>whore</hi> is two-fould<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 1. <hi>Oppoſing;</hi> 2. <hi>Exalting;</hi> both which you may fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> attributed to <hi>Anti-chriſt,</hi> or the <hi>Whore:</hi> in tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2, 4. ſhe appoſeth <hi>Chriſt</hi> or <hi>God;</hi> and therefore called <hi>Anti-chriſt:</hi> Now ſee O man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> whether this <hi>Whore</hi> be not thy fleſhly <hi>wiſdome</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> look into thy ſoul, and behold and ſee, how oppoſite thy fleſhy wiſdome, is to any thing that is good or goodneſs: what meanes thoſe often reſiſtings of the <hi>Spirit</hi> in thee, O man? Seeſt thou not how the <hi>whore</hi> deceives thee? What <hi>conception, bringing forth,</hi> or <hi>appearance</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is there in thee, but the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of the <hi>fleſh,</hi> ſeeks to devour it, by violent attempts &amp; op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, therefore the text ſaith <hi>ver.</hi> 17.6. <hi>That the whore was drunk with the bloud of the Saints; and Martyres</hi> of <hi>Jeſus:</hi> How hath this myſticall <hi>whore</hi> the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of the <hi>fleſh, martyred</hi> the appearances of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>thee,</hi> ſo that indeed ſhe is drunk with the bloud of many a ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied motion of the <hi>Spirit</hi> in thee? The <hi>wiſdome</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:107173:8"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the <hi>fleſh</hi> is, that myſticall <hi>Saul,</hi> that hunts ſf ter the bloud of <hi>David;</hi> which is, the tender <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppearance of <hi>God</hi> in the ſoul; this it is that ſucifieth the <hi>Lamb</hi> a freſh, and puts him to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n ſhame; and all this is done by that blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>whore</hi> that harboureth in thy boſome.</p>
            <p>The wiſdome of the fleſh is, that bond-ſlave, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at alwaies preſents <hi>wisdomes Children</hi> and the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ildren of the free Woman;</hi> which are the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gs forth of <hi>Jeſus</hi> in thee; In a word, this is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at <hi>great Red Dragon,</hi> ſpoken of in <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.3, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> who ſtands before the <hi>Woman;</hi> which is, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>riſtian, under the panges of the new birth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ady to be delivered of the bleſſed <hi>child Jeſus;</hi> whoſe hart, God is begetting himſelf, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> own forme and Image: this I ſay, is that <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>agon,</hi> even the wiſdone of the fieſh, which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dy to devour the ſweet <hi>Babe,</hi> even <hi>Jeſus,</hi> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> forme and feature in the ſoule, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rs to make it an obhortive:</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>is is that <hi>miſticall Heroad,</hi> that ſeekes the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>of the appearance of God in our fleſh: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s you ſee what the oppoſing nature of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore</hi> is; who for her bloudy oppoſition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnſt the manifeſtations of God in his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhall have blood to drinke, when ſhee ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound worthy.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. We now proceed to the other qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of the Nature of this <hi>whore;</hi> which is, a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107173:9"/>High, Proud, Lofty, aſſpiring Nature; bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> manifeſted by two things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that ſhe will get into Gods <hi>Temple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4. 2. In that ſhe will therein exa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her ſelf above all that is called God, and ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will be a god to her ſelf: Behold O man! (a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it were in a glaſs) the true Viſeognime an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perfect Portrature of thy fleſhly wiſdome.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, conſider, that thy heart is tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Temple of God, where this <hi>great Whore</hi> ſiteth therefore, minde the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yee not that yee are the Temple of God;</hi> as alſo <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 6.19. Now, thou being this Temple of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thy fleſhly wiſdome is that <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Whore,</hi> that ſits in thine hart; thou art th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Beaſt,</hi> that this <hi>Whore</hi> rides upon, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.12. that <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> being in honour, abideth not; but is like the heaſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> periſheth:</hi> here mayeſt thou ſee, O man! the pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the wiſdome of the fleſh, that no plac wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſerve her, but Gods Temple the hart of ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that God hath ſet apart for <hi>the praiſe of his glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> doth this Whore make her Beaſt, by bringi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it to be ſubject to her dominion; this Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, tobe that den of the every: whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> God hath made for his own honour and di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the exalting Nature of the <hi>who</hi> is ſeen, not only by her climing up into <hi>Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:107173:9"/>Temple,</hi> and ſo becomes that <hi>Lucifer,</hi> that fell down to <hi>hell:</hi> but alſo by her <hi>behaviour</hi> in Gods <hi>Temple; She exalts her ſelf above all that is called God;</hi> She ſits as God in Gods <hi>Temple,</hi> in a place where She hath no right to Rule and governe:</p>
            <p>Behold here, O Chriſtian! another proper Emblem of the wiſdome of the fleſh in thee: How doth this <hi>Whore,</hi> this <hi>Miſticall Babylon</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt her ſelf above every appearance of God in thee; in ſo much as <hi>her Tayle drawes the third part of the Stars of Heaven, and caſts them down to the Earth,</hi> which is in me? That Reaſon, Will, Affections and Judgement, which are as the civill powers &amp; lights of the ſoule, all theſe are drawn after this <hi>beaſt:</hi> ſo that indeed, Shee now is the <hi>Lady of the Kingdomes, Jſa.</hi> 47.7. nay, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>I am, and there is non elſe beſides mee:</hi> this wiſdome of the fleſh is that which will not alow the <hi>Child Jeſus</hi> any room in the Inne of thy heart: but thruſts him into the <hi>Manger;</hi> which is, under the meaneſt thoughts, pooreſt reſpects, and loweſt love of thy ſoule: but in the mean time, this <hi>whore</hi> her ſelf takes the largeſt rooms, and higheſt chambers; that is, She is moſt ſupreame in thy affections; with the greateſt love, honour, and reſpect that may bee: thus doth this <hi>whore</hi> the wiſdome of the fleſh, exalt her ſelf as God; yea, and that in Gods <hi>Temple;</hi> where She hath no right to rule
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107173:10"/>and govern; for the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tels us that <hi>wee ar not our owne: but are bought with a Price;</hi> that is, wee are to owne no <hi>Lord,</hi> but hee that hath bought us: to render no obedience or ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to any, but to that God who in our fleſh hath Redeemed us; according to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt have none other gods but<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e:</hi> but ſelf, fleſh, and creature will bee God in Gods Kingdome; which cauſeth God to take up a complaint againſt his people of old; <hi>Have I beene a barren wilderneſs unto thee; or a Land of darkneſs; wherſore then ſay my people, we are Lords, wee are Lords? and we will come no more after thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the creature running aſtray from the Lord, commits fornication with the <hi>great Whore</hi> the wiſdome of the fleſh; attributing all Power, Glory, Salvation and happineſſe, to ſelfiſh wiſdome: and therefore Babylon ſaith on this wiſe, <hi>Jſa.</hi> 14.13. <hi>I will aſcend into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; I will exalt my throne above the Stars of God:</hi> which is, when the wiſdome of the fleſh is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted above the higheſt ſphere of <hi>divine</hi> light in the ſoule: nay, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. <hi>I will be like the moſt High.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold O man! the aſpiring, exalting na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of thy carnall wiſdome: The wiſdome of the <hi>Serpent</hi> would needs have <hi>Adam</hi> to be as God; and to ſee by his own eyes, and to walk by his own <hi>light;</hi> which <hi>Serpent</hi> is nothing in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107173:10"/>the Myſtery but the wiſdome of the fleſh, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying the ſoul above that centre that <hi>God</hi> hath ſeated it in; cauſing thee to walke by her blaze, and not in <hi>Gods</hi> light to ſee light; to hate, ſcorn, and put a meane eſtimation upon any motion of God or goodneſſe; always thinking thy way the beſt, and thy councell the ſafeſt; and thus doth this <hi>Whore</hi> thy fleſhly wiſdome, exalt her ſelf above all that is called <hi>God</hi> in thee; and ſits as <hi>God</hi> in thy ſoule, which is <hi>Gods Temple.</hi> So much for anſwer to the firſt queſtion; namly, what this <hi>great whore</hi> is.</p>
            <p>Now thou, having attained ſome ſpirituall diſcovery of this <hi>whore,</hi> both by her <hi>Names</hi> and <hi>Nature;</hi> it remains, that we proceede in anſwer to the ſecond queſtion: which is, Namely;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How this Whore workes, and what pretences Shee deludes the ſoule by:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now therefore, know O man! that this <hi>whore</hi> workes in a <hi>miſtery; upon her Fore-head is written Miſtery, Rev.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>When Antichriſt, or thy fleſhly wiſdome is moſt apparant in any ſinfull action; yet in that appearance, She is very <hi>Miſticall:</hi> So that ſindeede, upon her moſt open workings in the heart; there is written <hi>Miſtery:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a property of a Strumpet to pretend what ſhee doth not intend to her Lovers: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old a Character of the <hi>Mother of Harlots,</hi> thy
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107173:11"/>fleſhly wiſdome; <hi>She is very ſubtill of heart; Prov.</hi> 7. She alwaies pretends, what ſhee never intends: So that here, all is well in the Hiſtory; but meare deceit and deluſion in the <hi>Miſtery:</hi> this <hi>whore,</hi> Shee will preſent a glorious ſhew; but there is nothing but wickedneſſe and Harlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try intended:</p>
            <p>This is that <hi>Spirituall Judas,</hi> that will Betray thee with his ſalutations: you ſhall find this <hi>whore</hi> in a religious <hi>Dreſs,</hi> many times; that hereby ſhe may deceive the heart of the ſimple: <hi>Obſerve</hi> how the <hi>Harlot</hi> in <hi>Prov.</hi> 7. beguiled the yong Man; <hi>She caught him, and Kiſſed him; ver.</hi> 13. <hi>and with an impudent face, ſaide unto him; I have peace Offerings with me; this day I have paid my vowes:</hi> this <hi>whore</hi> in the <hi>Miſtery,</hi> is thy fleſhly wiſdome; and thou art this <hi>ſimple young Man;</hi> who art deluded by her. Behold therefore, O man! the impudency, and bouldneſs of this <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Whore;</hi> She is not aſhamed to ſhew her Fore-head to thee: But here is a Miſtery all this while, that thou ſeeſt not.</p>
            <p>Now therefore know, Oh Chriſtian! that this <hi>whore</hi> appeares to thee in all thy ſpirituall performances &amp; Sacrifices to the <hi>Lord:</hi> if thou doeſt but obſerve, thou ſhalt ſee her appeare in Prayer, in Humiliation, in Faſting; nay, in all outward Ordinances; thou ſhalt ſee thy fleſhly wiſdome in all theſe things, ſteale thy
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107173:11"/>heart from the <hi>Lord,</hi> by attributing ſomthing to form, fleſh, and creature: ſo that wee are apt oft-times to bleſſe our ſelves in our ſpirituall performances, and ſing a <hi>Requiem</hi> to our ſelves in our fleſhly formes; ſo that hereby, all our duties are but the <hi>Sacrifices</hi> of the <hi>Whore,</hi> the <hi>vowes</hi> of our fleſhly wiſdome, which She ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in, to delude us:</p>
            <p>Now, woe and alas for us! that ever wee ſhould be deceived by this <hi>whore,</hi> in thoſe things wherein we think is leaſt appearance of her; but here is plainly ſeen her <hi>miſticall</hi> apparition:</p>
            <p>This <hi>whore</hi> meets thee, O man! in all thy religious performances; and there doth She attribute all the goodneſſe of all that is done, to her ſelf; and thou alſo giveſt conſent to it; and to commit Fornication with her: hence it is that the <hi>woman</hi> is ſaide, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. to have a <hi>Golden Cup in her hand, full of abominations, &amp; fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs of her fornications;</hi> a golden Pot, but a bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter potion.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Serpent,</hi> our fleſhly wiſdome, appeares to us with her ſpeckled Skin; but within her, there is deadly Poyſon: Beware then of this <hi>whore,</hi> in all her glorious appearances, and golden manifeſtations; for all this is but to inſnare thy heart with her treachery: the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the fleſh will meete thee many times arrayed in <hi>Purple,</hi> and <hi>Scarlet;</hi> coloured, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107173:12"/>deck'd with Gold; which in the <hi>Miſtery,</hi> are nothing elſe but ſhewes of glory to thee: She will meet thee in good performances; &amp; there ſhee will ſalute thee; and tell thee that thy good duties have prevailled with <hi>God</hi> for thee; and She will tell thee, becauſe thou art under ſuch an outward forme, and carnall diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that therefore thou art better then other Chriſtians, which injoy <hi>God</hi> in a more <hi>ſpiritual</hi> making out of himſelf: thus She will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make thee drink of her <hi>Fornication,</hi> by propoſing her <hi>golden Cup</hi> to thee: and thus poore ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>duced man, commits folly with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; or his own wiſdome in all outward wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip whatſoever, forſakes <hi>God,</hi> in praying, faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, mourning, and all outward formes; and is carried away more with the decency, order and trimneſſe of the <hi>whore,</hi> in an outward diſpenſation; then the Power and life of <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> requires in a Chriſtian: and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much ſhall ſuffice for the ſetting forth of the firſt <hi>deluſive pretence</hi> of the <hi>Whore;</hi> which is, to array her ſelf in her glory, the better to effect her deſigne upon the poore creature.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The deſigne of <hi>Anti-chriſt,</hi> or thy fleſhly wiſdome, is alwaies to bring thee out of love with <hi>God:</hi> O! its death to the <hi>whore,</hi> when ſhee ſeeth that thou deſireſt to bee conſtant to thy Husband <hi>Jeſus;</hi> who hath eſpouſed thee to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:107173:12"/>himſelf; and therefore, <hi>She</hi> is ſtill labouring to bring thee out of love with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>God:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this She labours to effect, by cauſing of thee to think that <hi>God</hi> doth not love thee; that ſo hereby, She might eſtrange thy heart from the <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the worke of this <hi>Serpent,</hi> to raiſe in our hearts hard thoughts of <hi>God:</hi> all poore afflicted ſoules, whoever you are that grieve under the pangs of an accuſing conſcience; harken, behold and conſider! how the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the fleſh deludes you, by cauſing you to looke upon <hi>God</hi> in the glaſſe of fleſh and creature; and ſo hereby, to apprehend him to be what he is not:</p>
            <p>Poore ſoule, thou telleſt me there is no mercy in a <hi>Chriſt</hi> for thee; and prithee why ſo? Oh, Alas! <hi>God</hi> loves me not, hee is offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at me, and diſpleaſed with me; I have beene ſo vile a ſinner againſt him.</p>
            <p>Now all this while, the poore ſoul doth but looke upon <hi>God</hi> according to the dictates of ſelfiſh wiſdom; and ſo it apprehends <hi>God</hi> to bee like it ſelf: <hi>Thou thougheſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>God</hi>) <hi>that I had been altogether ſuch a one as thy ſelfe:</hi> Becauſe we are angry with <hi>God</hi> many times, therefore we are apt to thinke <hi>God</hi> is froward with us; whereas, <hi>God is love,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle; Eph.</hi> 1. <hi>John,</hi> 4. and therefore <hi>God</hi> tells us, that <hi>his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107173:13"/>thoughts are not our thoughts, nor our waies, his ways; Jſa.</hi> 55.</p>
            <p>The wiſdome of the fleſh eudeavours to put out, and extinguiſh the light of <hi>God</hi> in a Chriſtian; whereby the ſoul might ſee <hi>God</hi> to be purely Love and mercy; and will propoſe its own glaſſe to the creature; which renders <hi>God</hi> to be what he is not, to mans apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion:</p>
            <p>So that when the ſoul would fain be refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with the comfortable aſpect of <hi>Gods</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; then comes fleſhly wiſdom, &amp; tels the <hi>ſoul</hi> it muſt not behold <hi>God</hi> according to his <hi>Love;</hi> but according to its own Iniquity; and ſo here by, daſheth the ſoule upon the rock of deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; in ſo much that the poore creature now concludes, that <hi>God</hi> is angry with him, and is reſolved not to ſhew him mercy.</p>
            <p>Now when the <hi>Whore</hi> hath thus eſtranged the heart from the <hi>Lord,</hi> by perſwading the ſoul, that either, <hi>God</hi> is not able, or willing to help it in its miſery: then She propoundes her own way to the creature; She will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the creature never to goe to <hi>God</hi> againe; but rather with the <hi>Prodigall,</hi> to goe and feede upon the <hi>Husks;</hi> as namely, upon Prayer, faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or ſome outward and carnall Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: and here the ſoule eſtranged from the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> commits Adultery with the <hi>Whore,</hi> in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107173:13"/>ſubſiſting on the Shadow; forſaking the <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> runing to the broken Ciſternes; and ſo commits a great evill againſt the Lord: and thus poore naked man runnes from God, as from an enemie, behind the trees of his own creating; and before he will bee beholding to God for a clothing, hee will cover him-ſelf with the <hi>Figleaves</hi> of his own fleſhly wiſdome, and ſo commits Adultery with the Mother of <hi>Harlots:</hi> and now thou ſeeſt another deluſive pretence of the <hi>whore,</hi> by raiſing hard thoughts of God in thee, by bringing thee out of love with the <hi>Lord</hi> thy Husband; that ſo She might the better ſteale thy heart from <hi>God</hi> and Rob him of his due and propriety.</p>
            <p n="3">3 This <hi>Mother of Harlots,</hi> thy fleſhly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom wil propoſe her ſelf to be all to thee, that ſo She may draw thy affections after her; Shee will tell thee that ſhe can ſupply all thy wants and relieve al thy neceſſities, and therfore thou needeſt not to bee beholden to God for any thing; She will tell thee with <hi>Adam,</hi> that She can give thee the knowledge of good &amp; evill; and ſhe can open thy eyes, &amp; She it is that gives thee any thing; therefore the text ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.13. <hi>A fooliſh Woman is Clamorous, She is ſimple and knowes nothing:</hi> this fooliſh Woman is thy fleſhly wiſdome, O man! for the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith <hi>The wiſdome of the fieſh is fooliſhneſs with the Lord:</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:107173:14"/>which although it bee fooliſh, ſimple and to knowes nothing, yet She is very <hi>clamorous;</hi> that is, her voice muſt chiefly be harkened un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> if the <hi>ſtill, ſmall voice of the ſpirit</hi> utter if ſelf in thy Soul, how doth the clamour of thy foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh fleſhly wiſdome as it were out-cry, and drown the utterings of <hi>God</hi> in thee; therfore the <hi>Text</hi> ſaith <hi>ver.</hi> 14. that <hi>She ſits in the dore of her houſe, and the higheſt Places of the City, to call Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers who go right in their way; who ſo is ſimple let him turn in hither, and as for him that wants under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, She ſaith; Stollen waters are ſweet, &amp; bread eaten in ſecret is pleaſant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas! poore ſelf ſeduced man that reads this Hiſtory, and ſeeſt not that thou thy ſelf art the very perſon intended; know therefore that thou art this paſſenger, who whil'ſt thou art travelling right on thy way to ſeek after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> art deluded by the clamour of this <hi>ſtrange Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> whileſt thou art ſeeking after <hi>wiſdome,</hi> She bids thee turn in hither, ſhe hath wiſdome and knowledge for thee; although indeed ſhee is ſimple and knowes nothing: <hi>Oh Sirs!</hi> how wiſe would ſelf be, when it is nothing but fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the <hi>abſtract.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus O man! thou art invited to <hi>Babylons</hi> banquet, &amp; runneſt after the <hi>ſtollen waters of the Whore,</hi> thy fleſhly wiſdome; which ſtollen wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, in the <hi>Miſtery,</hi> are nothing elſe but the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:107173:14"/>depriving of <hi>God</hi> of his due in all his workes in the ſoule; when <hi>God</hi> brings forth his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and divine light, in the ſoul, then fleſh and ſelf will tell thee that all proceeds from them; and ſo ſteale <hi>Gods</hi> propriety from him; and thus, Man runs from <hi>God</hi> and is eſtranged from the Lord, and eates his bread ſecretly with the <hi>harlot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this (in my apprehenſion) is a <hi>third</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſive pretence of the <hi>whore,</hi> ſo to ſhew her ſelf to the creature as if all fulneſſe were treaſured in her; in whom indeed is nothing but vacancy and emptineſſe: thus doth this <hi>whore</hi> draw us from the Lord, our lover; who hath ever bin conſtant to us, and that in the very height of our inconſtancy to him.</p>
            <p>It is the deſigne of <hi>God</hi> in us, to bring us to live upon his fulneſſe, and to feed upon thoſe <hi>divine</hi> dainties which hee will carve out to us: and what ſoul is it, that in the time of his conſtancy to the Lord ever wanted any thing? nay, what ſpirituall refreſhments and incomes of divine glory have our ſouls taſted of, while we have kept in our <hi>Fathers houſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when once <hi>Jeſhurem</hi> waxeth fat, and kicks; when once we, <hi>prodigall like,</hi> forſake our <hi>Father,</hi> and think that there is enough in ſelfe and creature to ſubſiſt upon: when once we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to loath the <hi>Heavenly Manna, Chriſt Jeſus,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:107173:15"/>and to eſteme more of the Fleſh-pots, Garlick and Onyons of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> the raw and ranck diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of this <hi>Whore,</hi> of <hi>bondage</hi> in us; when we prefer the <hi>husks</hi> of <hi>Swiniſh</hi> ſelf, and wiſdome, before the <hi>dainties of our Fathers Table;</hi> truly we ſhall at laſt come to know the want of divine joy and comfort:</p>
            <p>Know therfore, <hi>O Man!</hi> that in all thy wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings from the Lord <hi>thy full fountain,</hi> to ſelfe thy broken ciſtern; thou in the mean time, art drawne by the <hi>whore</hi> thy fleſhly wiſdome, to yeild to her wickedneſſe, <hi>by her flattering lips She forceth thee, Prov.</hi> 7.21. and thou goeſt after her as a ſilly <hi>Oxe</hi> to the <hi>ſlaughter, till a Dart ſtrike through thy Liver,</hi> which dart is one of the <hi>fiery darts</hi> which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeakes of; even the woundings of conſcience, the <hi>gnawings of the Worme</hi> in thee: And this is that <hi>ſpirituall death,</hi> which thou haſt brought upon thy ſelf, by commiting <hi>Adultery</hi> with the <hi>whore,</hi> thy fleſhly wiſdome; who hath ſtolen thy heart from the <hi>Lord,</hi> by atributing all fullneſs to her ſelfe in thee; and now She leaves thee, as not being able to help thee in thy woe, diſtreſs and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: and ſo much ſhall ſuffice for the diſcovery of a third deluſive pretence of the <hi>whore;</hi> whereby Shee deceiveth the heart of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple man.</p>
            <p n="4">4 This <hi>Whore,</hi> the wiſdome of the fleſh is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:107173:15"/>very changeable in her appearances; it is the policy of a <hi>Harlot</hi> to ſute her ſelf to the <hi>humor</hi> and <hi>fancy</hi> of her <hi>Lovers;</hi> that ſo thereby Shee may ſtill retain and keepe them in her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour:</p>
            <p>Even ſo it is with the <hi>ſpirituall Whore,</hi> the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Harlots,</hi> thy fleſhly wiſdome; which will ſtill be moving and changing her ſelf in her appearances to thee, that ſo her deſigne may be carried on the more ſubtilly; therefore the <hi>Text</hi> ſaith <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Leaſt thou ſhouldeſt ponder the pathes of life, her wayes are moveable, thou can'ſt not know them:</hi> Behold here, as in a <hi>Glaſs,</hi> the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this <hi>whoriſh Woman,</hi> the wiſdome of the fleſh! how moveable is She in all the puttings forth of her ſelf to man; if thy heart leads thee to all manner of Palpable prophanneſs this <hi>whore</hi> will encourage thee to this courſe of life; and She will tell thee that there is time enough yet to be ſory for thy miſdeedes; and if through the <hi>motions</hi> of goodneſſe, thou beginneſt to Ponder of thy Wickedneſſe; and therefore art reſolved to mend thy wicked courſes, and to be more <hi>Morally Vertuous</hi> for the time to come: this <hi>Whore</hi> will move with thee hither alſo; She will lead thee forth to the preſence of many a good Morall action, as to extend <hi>Almes,</hi> to feed the Hungry, to Cloath the Naked, to Viſit the Sick, and to leave of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:107173:16"/>thy old Vices thou haſt formerly lived in; all this She will be well contented with: She will be willing with <hi>Saul,</hi> to <hi>kill part of the ſpoile,</hi> ſome open Vices and Palpable prophanneſſe; but <hi>Agag and the fatteſt of the Cattell,</hi> the chief luſts of thy heart, She will worke yet under; that in the <hi>Miſtery</hi> muſt be ſpared: thus the <hi>Whore</hi> will conform her ſelf to man; nay, if thou art brought by higher light, to ſee that <hi>Godlyneſs</hi> doth not conſiſt only in refraining from ſome open Vices, and imbracing their contrary Vertues; but there muſt be <hi>Religion,</hi> as wel as <hi>Morallity</hi> looked after: and therforenow thou art reſolved to take upon thee ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Profeſſion of Chriſtianity:</p>
            <p>This <hi>whore</hi> will change her appearances to thee here alſo; She will come forth to meet thee with her <hi>Peace Offering</hi> and her <hi>Vowes;</hi> She will move with thee to Faſting, Prayer, and Humiliation, provided, that all this while thou attribute the glory of all to her ſelf; She will move as high as any outward Ordinance with thee; and all this is leſt thou ſhouldeſt ponder the <hi>Path of life:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Leſt thou ſhouldeſt queſtion this <hi>whore</hi> in her Wanton <hi>geſture</hi> and gaudy <hi>Attire,</hi> She will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have her ſelf more Religiouſly, and Adorn her ſelf more demurely; that ſo hereby She may the more cunningly draw thy affections after
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:107173:16"/>her: and thus poore ſeduced Man is <hi>Miſtically</hi> miſ-led, by the flatteries of this <hi>whoreiſh Woman:</hi> and in the mean time he thinkes he ſerves <hi>God:</hi> &amp; this is a 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> pretence of the <hi>Mother of Harlots,</hi> to move and change in all her appearances to thee, that ſo by her conformity to thee in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very reſpect, She may yet keep thy affections intire to her ſelf.</p>
            <p n="5">5 It is the property of this <hi>ſtrange Woman,</hi> thy fleſhly wiſdome, to render <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be at a diſtance from thee, in all her fornications with thee:</p>
            <p>If Man in all his adulteries from the Lord, did but ſerioufly conſider &amp; really underſtand, that his firſt lover <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> is in him, and ſeeth him in all his ſtrayings from him; and how he eates his bread ſecretly, with the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the fleſh; ſurely he would bee aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of his folly, and would not dare thus to commit <hi>Harlotry</hi> in the ſight of his <hi>ſpirituall lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> and this the wiſdome of the fleſh knowes right-well: and therefore labours might and maine to render Chriſt at a diſtance from the creature; that ſo the ſoul might not be affraid to commit fornication with her.</p>
            <p>Therefore, it is the <hi>Language</hi> of the <hi>whore, Prov.</hi> 7.19.20. <hi>The good-man is not at whome, he is gone into a far country;</hi> and behold the Language of this Miſticall Strumpet, the wiſdome of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:107173:17"/>fleſh! She wil perſwade thee that thou mayeſt take alittle liberty to ſin, that thou mayeſt exalt ſelf alittle, in religious performances; for <hi>God</hi> ſeeth thee not, he is in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and not in thy heart: and thus, Man being deluded by the flatteries of this <hi>Whore,</hi> becomes that Foole <hi>who hath ſaid in his hart there is no God;</hi> that ſo he might Magnifie, Diefie, and Worſhip ſelf in Gods ſtead:</p>
            <p>Self and fleſh will not owne the Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>God</hi> in the Soul, when the Lord lets forth the <hi>beames</hi> of his <hi>glory</hi> into the heart of man, and doth as it were draw up the ſoul to a higher Centre, by giving it ſome taſt of the <hi>Powers of the World to come:</hi> it is the worke of thy fleſhly wiſdome to extinguiſh this divine light in the ſoul, and as it were to corrupt the Stomack, and put the mouth out of taſt; that ſo it might not relliſh or digeſt thoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine dainties:</p>
            <p>And notwithſtanding thoſe open appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Chriſt in thee, yet, the wiſdome of the fleſh will tell thee, that the good man <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> is gone abroad, he is at a diſtance from thee: This <hi>Whore</hi> will be contented that thouth ſhouldeſt know any thing but Chriſt Jeſus <hi>and him Crucified</hi> in thee; She is willing that thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhouldeſt know Chriſt Naturally, but not <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually; Chriſt</hi> in the Hiſtory; but not in the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:107173:17"/>Myſtery; <hi>Chriſt</hi> for thee, but not Chriſt in thee: it is poſſible for a man to know very much of the fleſh of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to be acquainted with the Hiſtory of Godlyneſſe, to live under carnall Ordinances and fleſhly diſpenſations, to talke and diſpute upon high Principles, to be higher in the underſtanding of the <hi>Scriptures</hi> then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by the Head and ſhoulders with <hi>Saul;</hi> and yet for all this, he may in all theſe things commit Adultery with the <hi>whore;</hi> all theſe things may be to him no more, then the <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and the Vowes of this ſpirituall Whore,</hi> the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the fleſh: he is not the true Profeſſor, therefore, that can Read, Heare, Faſt and Pray, and Worſhip <hi>God</hi> in an outward diſpenſation; but thoſe are the true <hi>Circumciſion</hi> that Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <hi>God in the Spirit, and rejoyce in</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>and have no confidence in the fleſh:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He is not a Chriſtian indeed, that doth by the power of nature, believe what is Naturally and Hiſtorically reported of Chriſt in the Scripture, but he that by the power of the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> beleeves all this Hiſtory to be verified in him in the <hi>Myſtery:</hi> for there is a Hiſtory, and a <hi>Myſtery</hi> of Chriſt; the Hiſtory is <hi>Chriſt for us,</hi> the Myſtery is <hi>Chriſt in us, Col.</hi> 1.27.</p>
            <p>Now that Power of Nature which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted in man, is ſufficient for the giving credit to whatſoever Chriſt is, or hath been
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:107173:18"/>for us, but not for what Chriſt is in us; this muſt be by a power equall with that which raiſed up Jeſus from the dead, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1,</p>
            <p>Thy fleſhly wiſdome will bee contented thou ſhouldeſt be acquainted with what Chriſt hath done for Thee, but She will not endure to let Thee ſee him in Thee:</p>
            <p>Firſt, She is willing to let Thee underſtand that Chriſt hath been made <hi>fleſh</hi> for Thee, but not that <hi>the word is made fleſh</hi> in Thee; that is, that this God hath by his own power begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten himſelf, and brought forth himſelf in his owne likenes in Thee; that thou art this <hi>virgin</hi> that is <hi>over-ſhaddowed with power from on High;</hi> and haſt the <hi>immortall ſeed</hi> of God in Thee; which Immortall Seed by its owne power; brings forth its owne ſelfe in thy ſoul; by the puttings forth of the <hi>motions</hi> of the <hi>ſpirit in thee:</hi> this thy fleſhly wiſdome will not let Thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the wiſdome of the fleſh in that Serpent, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.15. that caſts out his <hi>flood after the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> or a Chriſtian, in whome Chriſt is by the power of the Spirit borne and brought forth; this flood in the <hi>Myſterie</hi> is, nothing in me, but the over-flowing of the wiſdome of the fleſh, the inundations of finfull ſelf and creature, that flow into the heart of man; this Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Serpent,</hi> hereby endevouring to drown and deſtroy, both Chriſt and a Chriſtian, at once
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:107173:18"/>as it were; both the Paſſive <hi>Mother,</hi> and the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Babe</hi> on a ſuddain; ſuch an enemy is the wiſdome of the fleſh to Chriſt in us:</p>
            <p>This flood of iniquity, theſe over-flowings of the wiſdome of the fleſh in us, is that great <hi>River Euphrates,</hi> that muſt be dried up, that way may bee made for <hi>the King of the Eaſt,</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, to ruinate <hi>great Babell</hi> in mans heart: and thus you ſee briefly, how the wiſdome of the fleſh is an enemy to Chriſt borne in us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. She cannot endure to let us ſee the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Chriſt in us; although wee are the very Perſons that Crucifieth the <hi>Lambe</hi> a freſh, and put him to <hi>open ſhame;</hi> yet She will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us otherwiſe: and thus poore ſelf-ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced man, Crucifies his <hi>Saviour</hi> every day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh; and yet is ſo deluded by him-ſelfe, that he ſeeth it not:</p>
            <p>Conſider then O man, that thou art this Spirituall <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where Chriſt is ſlaine; thou art that Judge, that condemneſt Chriſt in the <hi>motions</hi> of his Spirit; &amp; letteſt <hi>Barabhas,</hi> or thy baſe luſts, goe uncontrouled: all the faculties of thy ſoul, and the powers of the inner-man, miſ-led by the wiſdome of the fleſh, are as it were the voice of the People, Crucifie him, Crucifie him: thy ſins are thoſe <hi>ſpeares</hi> that Pierce Chriſt in ſpirit, in thee: and thus O man! thou art the dayly Croſſe of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:107173:19"/>thy <hi>Saviour:</hi> and how happy ſhouldeſt thou bee if thou did'ſt diſcerne all this; that ſo thou mighteſt looke upon him whom thou now <hi>pierceſt</hi> and <hi>mourn</hi> for thy iniquity: but the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of this <hi>whore,</hi> thy fleſhly wiſdome, is to darken thy eye from beholding of this; She will rather tell thee, that the <hi>good man is not at home,</hi> Chriſt is not in thee in his <hi>Sufferings:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus poore man, miſ-led by the <hi>Whore,</hi> becomes that deceitfull <hi>Pilate</hi> that waſheth his hands of the <hi>blood</hi> of this innocent Spirit, whom it hath diſpitefully Crucified.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, Chriſt may be ſaid to dye in a Chriſtian another way: which alſo this <hi>whore</hi> cannot endure we ſhould ſee and behold; and that is, when Chriſt dyes in fleſh to us, and in us; for ſome times Chriſt lives in fleſhly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of him ſelf in a Chriſtian; ſome Chriſtians, the higheſt diſcovery of Chriſt that they have attained unto, is fleſhly formes, and fleſhly Ordinances; &amp; thus many a <hi>chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> enjoyes Chriſt as really, and as comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably, as the <hi>Diſciples</hi> did the Naturall fleſh of Chriſt; now Chriſt he would needs dye, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, goe away from his <hi>diſciples</hi> in the fleſh, that ſo hee might come in a higher, and more glorious diſpenſation to them; even ſo, oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Chriſt doth likewiſe dye in a chriſtian, to all outward and fleſhly diſpenſations: and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:107173:19"/>this death the wiſdome of the fleſh cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure that the ſoul ſhould diſcerne; how often doth God goe out of all low appearances to a Chriſtian? Inſomuch that a poor Chriſtian many times, can finde no Chriſt in his forms, no comfort in ordinances, no joy in duties and performances; but with <hi>Mary,</hi> ſtands <hi>weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Sepulchre,</hi> or thoſe dead diſpenſations where Chriſt is buried; and can ſee no appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of <hi>Jeſus</hi> in them; but all this while it <hi>ſeeks the living amongſt the dead:</hi> &amp; thus Chriſt dies in a Chriſtian to all fleſhly appearances, many times: And truly, looke what ſorrow fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſpirits of the poore <hi>diſciples,</hi> for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of their <hi>Lord</hi> (in the fleſh) from them; the like ſorrow and griefe, falls upon that Chriſtian, from whom Chriſt is departed in all outward diſpenſations:</p>
            <p>Chriſt compares that preſent eſtate and condition of the <hi>diſciples,</hi> to a Woman in Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.21, 22. <hi>and yee now therefore have forrow,</hi> ſaith Chriſt: Behold O Chriſtian, the lively Image of our condition! when Chriſt crucifies his own fleſh to us, in all thoſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſpenſations, wherein formerly wee have injoyed God.</p>
            <p>Happily, heretofore we have ſeen much of God in our outward formall fellowſhips one with another, in fleſhly Ordinances; as Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:107173:20"/>of water, and breaking of bread; but now happily Chriſt is crucified in all theſe things to us; and wee finde nothing but dead fleſh there; nothing that can <hi>adminiſter</hi> any ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall comfort in any of theſe things; ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but forme &amp; bare Fleſh, bare Water, bare Bread, and Wine; in ſo much that wee now confeſſe, that our higheſt attainments of the knowledge of Chriſt, hath been but a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge after the fleſh; now here lyes Chriſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified to all theſe things, &amp; the ſoul dead to its wonted diſcoveries:</p>
            <p>Now the deſigne of thy Fleſhly wiſdome, is to darken this death of Chriſt in Thee; Shee cannot endure that the Soul ſhould move out of its fleſhly diſcoveries; for She loves the outward order, and fleſhly decency of all theſe things; and therefore She'l tell Thee, that Chriſt muſt be found here, or no where; and thus keep the Soul in bondage to her ſelf; in ſo much, that the poore creature goes again and againe to his outward worſhip, and yet findes no living Chriſt there; nor is poſſeſſed with any more comfort in them, then proceeds from the power of the fleſh; wheras indeed the Soul ſhould bee willing to waite in this dead condition, for the returne of the Spirit; to lye empty and bare at the gate of <hi>mercy,</hi> out of all thoſe formall diſpenſations, from
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:107173:20"/>whence Chriſt is departed; waiting for the <hi>Comforter:</hi> and therefore my councell is, to all thoſe who ſee Chriſt dead to all ſuch carnall and fleſhly diſpenſations in them: Chriſtian, wait upon the Lord and thou ſhalt renew thy ſtrength; Chriſt muſt have his time to lye in the <hi>grave,</hi> hidden from thee in all his appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances to thee; but this know, he will ſee thee againe, in a more Spirituall diſcovery of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; it is but a while, and he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry; and will take thee up into himſelfe, above theſe Types and Figures; hee will bee thy <hi>Water,</hi> and <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> to thee; hee will bring thee to the injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Subſtance, and thou ſhalt no more live upon the Shadow; thou ſhalt live up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the kernell, and not alwaies bee cracking upon the ſhell; <hi>For if wee be dead with Chriſt, wee ſhall allſo live together with him;</hi> but be ſure in the meane time, that thou beware of the <hi>Whore,</hi> leaſt She by her appearances to thee in all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Worſhips, make Thee believe that Chriſt is living in all thoſe things wherein he is dead and buried. And thus in briefe, you ſee that this Strumpet, the wiſdome of the fleſh, is an enemy to the diſcovery of Chriſt in us. And now me-thinks, by this time wee may ſee who is the <hi>great Anti-Chriſt</hi> that <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of, in his firſt <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 4. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>ver. That every ſpirit
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:107173:21"/>that believes not,</hi> or denies <hi>Chriſt come in the fleſh, is Anti-Chriſt:</hi> and what is it now, that denies Chriſt come in the fleſh? If thou wold'ſt know Chriſtian, what this <hi>Anti-chriſt</hi> is, and where She lyes; thou needeſt not goe far to diſcover it; thou needeſt not go to <hi>Rome, Canterbury,</hi> or <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> but thou mayeſt finde that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt in Thee, denying <hi>Jeſus</hi> to be come in thy fleſh:</p>
            <p>Oh, all ye that would faine ſhew your ſelves profeſſed enemies to this Antichriſt, that man of ſin; who ſeekes to deſtroy <hi>Roote</hi> and <hi>Branch,</hi> all thoſe in whom you conceive there are the appearances of him; Returne, Returne O man! into thy own Boſome; and there behold him lying ſecretly, in thy owne ſoul; there is the Antichriſt, that denies every manifeſtation of God in thy fleſh; this is the <hi>Whore</hi> that Thou daily commit'ſt Fornication with all; this is the <hi>Babilon,</hi> whoſe <hi>Down-fall</hi> will bee joyous to the Saints; this is the <hi>Heretick</hi> and the <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique;</hi> this it is that makes Rents and diviſions amongſt us: and therfore we ought every one of us, to deſire God to ſubdue the wiſdome of the fleſh in us; and to waite upon the Lord un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he comes to ſhew us the Judgement of the Spirituall <hi>Whore,</hi> this Antichriſt in us: and not ſo much deſire the down-fall of either Pope, Presbiter, or Independant, or any other
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:107173:21"/>State whatſoever; but to deſire the ruin of this <hi>Myſticall Babylon;</hi> which is the Mother of all our Harlotry from the Lord: And ſo much ſhall ſuffice for Anſwer to the Second queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is, Namly, how the <hi>Whore</hi> workes, and what Pretences She deludes the ſoule by?</p>
            <p>Wee proceed now in order to a third que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Namly,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>How the Soul comes to attaine to a ſight of her?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which, wee ſhall firſt propoſe <hi>the way that God doth uſually take to diſcover this Whore to a Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 When the Soul ſeeth her,, <hi>How and in what manner it apprehends her?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt for the way that a Soule comes to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a ſight of her by:</p>
            <p>If then, thou would'ſt know the way how a Chriſtian comes to a ſpirituall ſight of Fleſh and Selfe; know, that God muſt deale with Thee as hee did with <hi>John, Rev.</hi> 17. When God would ſhew <hi>John</hi> the Judgement of the <hi>great Whore,</hi> and give him a diſcovery of the <hi>whore;</hi> hee takes him <hi>ver.</hi> 3. <hi>and carrieth him away in the ſpirit, into the Wilderneſſe;</hi> and then ſaith <hi>John, I ſaw a Woman, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then know, that thou canſt never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſelf aright, till God take thee up, or cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thee away in the <hi>ſpirit;</hi> the <hi>ſpirituall man,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>ſeeth all things;</hi> diſcovers all
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:107173:22"/>things; and Judgeth all things: ſo much as the Lord ſpirituallizeth a Chriſtian, ſo much he ſees into himſelf, and diſcernes and beholds this <hi>Myſticall whore,</hi> the wiſdome of the fleſh, in himſelf: and now he judgeth and eſtemes of her as that <hi>whore,</hi> that Adultreſs with whom he hath (in all his waies and Worſhips) adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated from the Lord:</p>
            <p>Therefore the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, that <hi>the ſpirit ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all things,</hi> 2 <hi>Epiſt. Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> So long as the ſoul lyeth under the vaile of the fleſh, ſo long ſelfe is undiſcovered to him; for while the creature lyes wrapt up in the <hi>Mantle</hi> of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it is in a ſpirituall ſlumber or ſleep; and lyes as one paſſive, under the workings of the wiſdome of the fleſh; rock't a ſleep in the cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of fleſhly ſecurity: But now when God ſpeakes by the <hi>ſmall and ſtill voyce,</hi> yet powerfull utterance, of the Spirit in a Chriſtian; <hi>Come up hither;</hi> when God takes a Soul up beyonde ſelf and creature; in ſo much that now the creature ſees all but vanity, below Chriſt: now I ſay, the creature comes to ſome diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of himſelf; but never before.</p>
            <p>That man that will view the breadth and length of a City at once, muſt not alwaies be walking about in the ſtreets; but he muſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſay to get up to the top of ſome mountaine that lyes above it; and ſo the City ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:107173:22"/>to him, with its breadth and length: even ſo it is with the ſpirituall <hi>Babell,</hi> which is in thee Oh man! even the wiſdome of the fleſh: thou muſt bee taken above it ere thou canſt truly and really diſcover it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Thou muſt be carryed <hi>away in the ſpirit;</hi> carried quite away from all Power, Policy, Strength, Motion and Action of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</p>
            <p n="3">3 The place whither thou muſt bee carried; that is into a Wilderneſſe; which is, into a loſt condition, to ſin and ſelf: never doth the ſoule attain to a reall ſight of the fleſh, till the Lord by his Spirit doth (as it were) looſe the ſoule to it ſelf: when the creature comes to bee at a loſs in it ſelf, in all its fleſhly performances; not knowing where to have recourſe; but ſees that his narrow fleſhly heart, is ſo wide a wilderneſſe, that he is loſt in the many turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and windings thereof; now the creature comes to behold his <hi>Spirituall Adulteryes;</hi> now he ſees into what a loſt condition he is fallen; &amp; how the <hi>whore</hi> al this while, in all his duties, worſhips, formes and diſciplines, hath ſtolne his heart from the Lord, his firſt lover and tender Husband: <hi>Paul</hi> was carried away by the <hi>ſpirit</hi> into this Wilderneſſe, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 7, 8, 9. he profeſſeth <hi>ver.</hi> 7. <hi>That what things were gaine to him, he counted loſs for Chriſt; yea doubtleſſe,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:107173:23"/>ſaith he <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>and I count all things but loſs, for the excellency of Chriſt Jeſus my Lord, for whom I have ſuffered the loſs of all things, &amp; do count them but dung: that I may winne Chriſt: Paul never knew himſelf, nor creature excellency aright, till God ſhewed him the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the knowledge of Chriſt;</hi> and when hee comes to ſee the worth of Chriſt, then he ſee; himſelf in a <hi>wilderneſſe;</hi> and in this <hi>wilderneſſe,</hi> or loſt condition, hee ſpies the vanity of all that was fleſh below Chriſt; ſo that now when God carryes away a ſoul in the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and loſes it, as it were, to its ſelf; and lets looſe the <hi>beames of his owne glory</hi> upon it; raviſheth the heart with his own beauty, catcheth him up as it were into the third <hi>Heavens,</hi> and ſheweth ſuch divine excellency as it never yet appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended; the <hi>ſoul</hi> by the clear aſpect of this <hi>beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficall viſion</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> begins now to ſee the vanity and <hi>deformity</hi> of it ſelfe, and is (as it were) in as great amazement of <hi>ſpirit,</hi> as the man doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les was, who was <hi>borne blind from the womb,</hi> and yet now comes to ſee the <hi>Sun;</hi> or as one that hath been ſhut up in a dark <hi>Dungeon,</hi> and now comes to walke in the light, even thus it is with poor man in the higheſt glory and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the fleſh; when God ſends forth the <hi>beames</hi> of that <hi>Sun</hi> of righteouſneſſe upon poor <hi>Man,</hi> how dark he beholds himſelfe to be, as he ſtands in relation to all fleſhly excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:107173:23"/>when God ſhewes him the worth, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue and excellency of himſelfe in a Chriſt; what loſs dung and droſſe doth a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an eſteeme thoſe things to be, though former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly never ſo glorious and excellent; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Paul now no longer deſires to be found in his own excellency, or in himſelfe,</hi> but ſaith he <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>That I may be found in him, not having my owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which is by the Law; but that which is by the faith of the Son of God:</hi> the ſight of Chriſts excellency it doth ſo fully diſcover ſelf and fleſh to the Chriſtian, as that now he loaths the <hi>ſcarlet co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,</hi> the glorious atire of the <hi>Whore,</hi> even all its golden performances, <hi>her guilded vowes and ſacrifices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O all yee poor ſouls! who are apt to place your glory in any thing below Chriſt; and to hang your righteouſneſſe upon your <hi>Prayers, faſtings, mournings,</hi> or any outward Ordinances, alas, how far are you miſ-taken! who when the <hi>Lord</hi> comes to carry you away in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> to ſee all your glory in Chriſt, your righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in <hi>him;</hi> you will then ſee the odiouſneſſe of every thing below Chriſt, which thou haſt wondered after; thou wilt then deſire that <hi>God</hi> might find thee in this <hi>Wilderneſſe,</hi> quite out of <hi>ſelfe;</hi> that there may not be any <hi>hoofe</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> in thee; but that thou may'ſt wholy be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:107173:24"/>into Chriſt; in whom thou now ſeeſt thy glory to conſiſt: And thus you ſee, what the way is, that <hi>God</hi> uſeth to diſcover <hi>ſelf,</hi> or this <hi>Whore,</hi> the wiſdome of the fleſh, to the ſoul.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let us conſider how and in what manner the <hi>Soul</hi> beholds this <hi>Whore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A poor creature whom the <hi>Lord</hi> hath carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away, or taken up into the <hi>Spirit;</hi> that now lives &amp; walks in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> he ſees and beholds himſelfe, not as he was wont to doe formerly; happily thou waſt wont to ſee a glory and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency in things that were below <hi>God;</hi> but now on the contrary how loathſome is every thing, that comes ſhort of the divine excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Chriſt: happily heretofore thou haſt ſeen ſome worth in thy <hi>prayers,</hi> and in thy <hi>teares,</hi> ſome eſteemableneſſe in thy <hi>duties</hi> and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, ſome glory in thine own righteouſnes; but now thou ſeeſt all theſe things, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were counted gaine, to be but loſſe unto thee; thou beholdeſt all thy own righteouſnes to be but as a <hi>Menſtrous cloath, and as a filthy ragge:</hi> happily heretofore thou boaſteſt of thy <hi>pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree</hi> with <hi>Paul; of the Tribe of Benjamin, and of the ſtock of Iſrael;</hi> that thou art deſcended from ſuch a reformed <hi>Church;</hi> from ſuch viſible <hi>diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> ſo that as touching all legall <hi>worſhips,</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>formes</hi> and <hi>Ordinances,</hi> thou may'ſt be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:107173:24"/>a <hi>Phariſee;</hi> but now thou ſeeſt the lowneſſe, and weakneſſe of theſe <hi>fleſhly</hi> things, wherein thou haſt formerly boaſted; now thou rejoyceſt that thou haſt attained to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of that Chriſt, which is, the end or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of all theſe fleſhly things unto thee; ſo that now thou haſt no confidence in the fleſh any longer; but art become one of the true <hi>circumciſion, that worſhips God in the Spirit,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> in a word, this ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allized <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> ſeeth all below Chriſt to be but the garment of this ſpirituall <hi>Strumpet,</hi> that ſhe uſeth to appear in to deceive him; he now ſees the <hi>Whore,</hi> and her various pretences, and how ſhe hath formerly deceived him in her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall dreſſes; he ſees her not only in her gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy attire, but in the height of her <hi>modeſty,</hi> even in her religious <hi>garment;</hi> ſo that now he ſeeth how the wiſdome of the <hi>fleſh</hi> makes uſe of all outward <hi>worſhip, formes</hi> and <hi>Ordinances,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the heart of the ſimple.</p>
            <p>Finally this <hi>Spirituall Man,</hi> hath the ſame diſcovery of his <hi>whoriſh wiſdome,</hi> as <hi>John</hi> had, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17, from the 3, to the 7. <hi>ver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>John</hi> he ſaw the <hi>Woman</hi> ſitting upon a <hi>ſcarlet coloured Beaſt;</hi> truly when God carries thee away in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> thou wilt behold thy ſelfe to be the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> that this <hi>Myſticall whore,</hi> the <hi>wiſdom of the fleſh,</hi> doth thus <hi>vaſſallize</hi> man in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:107173:25"/>his <hi>fallen condition</hi> from <hi>God;</hi> as it were <hi>Satans Pack-horſe</hi> to act all his deſigns of wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Beaſt had ſeaven heads and ten hornes;</hi> theſe ſeven heads and ten hornes, <hi>are ſeven Mountaines and ten Kings</hi> the Scripture ſaith; which in me, are nothing but thoſe powers of man which <hi>God</hi> hath indued him withall; as <hi>Reaſon, Will, Affection, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>uderſtanding</hi> and the like; and all theſe <hi>ver.</hi> 13. <hi>doe with one conſent give and aſcribe their power to the Beaſt,</hi> or poor beaſtialized man; and this <hi>Beaſt</hi> man, imployes all theſe with their power to make war againſt the <hi>Lamb, Chriſt Jeſus, ver.</hi> 14. &amp; ſo here is a diſcovery of poor miſ-led <hi>Man,</hi> ſighting the battell of the <hi>Whore, his fleſhly wiſdome:</hi> all this doth the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian apprehend in himſelf, when the Lord car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries him away in the <hi>Spirit of</hi> his <hi>glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>John</hi> ſaw the <hi>Woman, ver.</hi> 4. <hi>arraied in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and ſcarlet colour, deck with Gold Pearles and precious Stones:</hi> Truly Chriſtian, when the Lord takes away this falce glaſſie eye of fleſh from thee, and endues thee with Spirituall eye-ſight from himſelf, thou ſhalt ſee this <hi>whore,</hi> thy fleſhly wiſdome in all this her glory and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency in Thee; for all theſe Golden Pearles and precious Stones, &amp; Scarlet colours, are but the trimmings of the <hi>whore,</hi> that She uſually puts on and cloathes her ſelf with all, when She comes out to meet the Sons of men; that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:107173:25"/>ſo hereby, She might with the more facillity dazle the eyes, infatuate and bewitch the ſences, of her Spirituall lovers: but now when God takes up a Soul into Spirit, then fleſh is as it were unclothed to the creature; and now the Soul lookes not at her glorious ſhewes, which formerly hath bewitched his heart; but he ſees and knowes that under that Golden habit, there walks this ſubtile Harlot; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Speckled Skin, there is a Venomous Viperous <hi>Serpentine</hi> Carkcas: the man whom God hath Spirituallized, when the wiſdome of the fleſh appeares in him in her glory, clad with excellency, and adorned with all her beautifull Robes; yet all this while he ſees her <hi>Naked and bare:</hi> the <hi>ſpirit</hi> teacheth him to looke inwardly, and not altogether outwardly: and this is ſuch a Myſtery that the poore carnall heart cannot diſcerne, becauſe he lookes fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and carnally; and hath not yet received this Spirituall eye-ſight from above.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But then, <hi>John ſaw the Woman having a gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Cup in her hand, full of abominations and filthynes of her Fornications:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that Soul which God wrapes up in that <hi>ſpirit of glory,</hi> he beholds this <hi>whore</hi> in him; and ſees how She hath deluded him by her <hi>gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Cup,</hi> to taſt of <hi>the wine</hi> of her Fornications; for this Golden Cup in the <hi>whores</hi> hand, is (in
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:107173:26"/>the Myſterie of it) the Guilded pretences, and Golden appearances of the wiſdome of the fleſh; in which pretences there is contained, the wickendeſſe of her abomination, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyneſſe of her fornication.</p>
            <p>A man catched up, and carried by the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> to walke in the light of Chriſt and to live in the purity of God, ſees him-ſelf (as it were) now awakened out of the drunken ſleep of the <hi>Whore;</hi> newly Riſen out of the <hi>defiled Bed</hi> of the fleſh; from the <hi>ſpirituall</hi> Vomits, Swiniſh abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, and Beaſtly uncleanneſſe that hee before wallowed in.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Againe <hi>John</hi> ſaw, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. what was <hi>written upon the Womans Fore-head:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly, untill ſuch time as the Lord takes a Soul up into <hi>ſpirit,</hi> though the wiſdome of the fleſh appeare openly to him, though She ſhewes her very <hi>Fore-head,</hi> yet hee cannot diſcerne her in her appearances; but now, when God hath caught the Soul into <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and carried him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in the <hi>ſpirit;</hi> then he ſees the <hi>whore</hi> in her apparitions; he beholds Myſterie in the <hi>Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,</hi> or palpable workings of the <hi>whore; My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery</hi> in all her ſpecious pretences: and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all her ſhewes of Glory; yet he ſees, She is indeed &amp; in truth <hi>Babylon the great:</hi> the great confuſed <hi>Whore,</hi> which breeds all that confuſion of ſpirit in a Chriſtian; all that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:107173:26"/>commotion, diſturbance, and out-cryes that are in the heart of man; all thoſe heavie, ſad and diſconſolate thoughts that man is poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all; all that diſorder that many a time is in the ſoul; every hard thought of God; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very diſpairing Imagination; all the gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of <hi>conſcience</hi> in the Creature: ſo that (I ſay) hee now ſees her to be that <hi>great Babel,</hi> or confuſed <hi>Whore,</hi> who is <hi>the Mother of Harlots, and Abominations of the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. But then laſtly, <hi>John ſaw the Woman drunke with the bloud of the Saints, and Martyrs of Jeſus:</hi> Truly, this is the very <hi>phiſiognome</hi> &amp; <hi>Portraiture</hi> of the <hi>whore,</hi> to a Chriſtian that is carriepaway in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> hee now comes to behold <hi>her</hi> a drunken bloud-thirſty <hi>Whore;</hi> he now ſeeth how the whore hath <hi>martyred</hi> the bringings forth of Chriſt, <hi>ſlain and crucified</hi> that <hi>Man Jeſus afreſh:</hi> he ſees how the <hi>Whore</hi> is drunk with <hi>the bloud of the Lamb in him:</hi> In a word, the <hi>Saint</hi> truly ſpirituallized, beholds ſelf and fleſh, to be the moſt hatefull, deteſtable, loathſome thing in the world to him; looke how loathſome and injurous a mans <hi>vomit</hi> is to his <hi>ſtomack,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo loathſome is <hi>ſelf</hi> to that Chriſtian; from whoſe <hi>ſtomack God</hi> hath fetched up all the corrupt fleſh, by bringing the ſoule to be love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> with the operative <hi>Pils</hi> of his bleſſed <hi>Spirit:</hi> O how hatefull now is the <hi>gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:107173:27"/>Cup &amp; ſweet Wine of the <hi>whore,</hi> to a <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuallized</hi> man; in ſo much that he now <hi>loathes</hi> and abhors himſelf in duſt and aſhes; nay, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he begins now to wonder at himſelfe, in his own ſhame and folly; as the <hi>Text</hi> ſaith, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. that when <hi>John</hi> ſaw the <hi>Whore</hi> he <hi>wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with great admiration;</hi> truly, the ſame is the condition of every <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> who by the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryings away of the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> comes to a <hi>ſpirituall</hi> ſight of this <hi>whore,</hi> the wiſdome of the fleſh; he now wonders that hee ſhould bee drawne to commit folly, by ſo filthy a <hi>Harlot:</hi> hee now wonders that ſuch a bulk of filthyneſſe, ſuch a Mountain of wickedneſſe, and ſpring of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe, ſhould be in him, and he never till now able to diſcerne it: he now wonders that ever the lenity and Mercy of God, ſhould ſo long beare with him in all his Adulteries with this ſwiniſh <hi>whore:</hi> he now wonders that God at laſt hath brought him to ſuch a ſight and diſocvery; he admires to ſee where he is, and where hee was; that God hath brought him from <hi>fleſh,</hi> to live in <hi>ſpirit;</hi> from darkneſſe, into <hi>his marvellous light;</hi> from the wayes of ſorow, to that <hi>high way,</hi> the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus you ſee, briefly, <hi>how, and in what manner, the Soul beholdes this Myſticall Whore, the wiſdome of the fleſh:</hi> And ſo much ſhall ſuffice for the third queſtion, Namely, <hi>how the creature comes to attaine to the ſight of her.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:107173:27"/>
            <p>Wee proceed now, in order to the fourth queſtion, which is, Namely,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When, and how She ſhall be deſtroyed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in brief, to <hi>Anſwer</hi> to this, and ſo draw to a concluſion of the matter; I thus reply,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> If then O man! thou deſireſt to know how, and when this <hi>ſpirituall Whore</hi> ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed: It ſhall be done in the <hi>day,</hi> and by the <hi>coming</hi> and appearance of <hi>Jeſus</hi> in Thee; this <hi>day</hi> is the <hi>laſt day;</hi> and this <hi>coming,</hi> is the <hi>ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of <hi>Jeſus:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as concerning this <hi>laſt day,</hi> know this O man! that its nothing for thee to reade the Hiſtory of the laſt day in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and there to ſee what ſhall be done in that <hi>day</hi> that God will <hi>glorifie himſelf in the Saints, and bee admired in all them that believe;</hi> that then <hi>God</hi> will <hi>through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purge his floore;</hi> and the Saints <hi>ſhall be like him, for they ſhall ſee him as he is:</hi> Now I ſay, it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to know this in the Hiſtory, except wee know it in the <hi>Myſterie</hi> of it:</p>
            <p>Thou art therefore to expect, <hi>Jeſus</hi> to come to Judgment in Thee; and the end of the <hi>world</hi> to bee in Thee: thou art to waite for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of this <hi>Jeſus</hi> in <hi>ſpirit;</hi> which ſhall come to thee as he did to <hi>John,</hi> and ſhew Thee <hi>the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great Whore</hi> in Thee; for there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that ſhall happen or fall out to thee, in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:107173:28"/>relation to the day of Judgement, which ſhall not bee verified in thee, in this life: though it may bee, not in the ſame mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtative meaſure or fulneſs, as it ſhall be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>As firſt, One ſign of this laſt day is, that there ſhall <hi>be wars, and rumors of warres, Nation ſhall riſe againſt Nation, &amp; Kingdome againſt Kingdome:</hi> now here Chriſtian thou mayeſt behold the laſt day to be at hand, here is <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> at battell with the <hi>Lamb;</hi> what is it that makes all that envy, variance, ſtrife, ſedition, emulation in the world, but the ſecond, or ſpiritual appearance of <hi>Je us</hi> in his People; the comming of Chriſt in his Saints, is not to bring <hi>peace, but a ſword</hi> amongſt us; I confidently ſay, that this laſt day, this ſpirituall appearance of Chriſt in men and women, is the very originall of all theſe commotions that are amongſt us; inſomuch that now here is, the <hi>Father hating the appearance of Chriſt in the Son,</hi> and the <hi>Son</hi> likewiſe in the <hi>Father;</hi> the <hi>Mother</hi> in the <hi>Daughter,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> in the <hi>Mother;</hi> one <hi>Brother</hi> ſheathing the <hi>ſword</hi> in the bowels of another, becauſe the laſt <hi>Day dawnes,</hi> and the <hi>Star</hi> of <hi>glory</hi> is riſen more in one then in another; her's <hi>Cain</hi> killing <hi>Abel,</hi> becauſe his <hi>ſacrifice is accepted of the Lord,</hi> and the other is not: I tell thee Chriſtian, the more the <hi>whore will beſtir her ſelf:</hi> ſhee will not only
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:107173:28"/>raiſe outward but inward warre againſt thee: which inward inſurrection and rebellion, is a ſymptome, that the day of <hi>Judgement is at hand in thee. John</hi> tells us <hi>Revel.</hi> 17, 14. <hi>That the kings of the earrh, ſhall make war againſt the Lambe;</hi> which Kings in the <hi>myſtery,</hi> are but the Kingly gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning powers of thy <hi>Soul,</hi> which are aſſembled together in thee to this <hi>Spirituall</hi> battell of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> to gage warre againſt the innocent Lamb <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> in Spirit: but the Lamb ſhall over come them, for he is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords; all the power and policy of the fleſh, ſhall at laſt yield their power to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſhall conſent to the juſt Judgement of the <hi>whore,</hi> thy fleſhly wiſdome; but till this ſtrong man the fleſh be caſt out, by that ſtronger then he, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> there will be nothing but war and confuſion in thee; ſo that indeed now the Serpent is come down with great rage in thee, knowing that he hath but a ſhort time; the more nigh the comming of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is, the more this Serpent ſpits out his venome; this <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> this <hi>whore</hi> will the more earneſtly beſtirre her ſelfe, knowing that it is but a ſhort time to her judgement. St. <hi>John</hi> tells us <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.7. <hi>That when the woman had brought forth her man childe which was to rule all Nations with a rodde of Iron,</hi> the woman upon the birth of this man childe fled into the wilderneſſe, and when the woman
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:107173:29"/>was in the wilderneſſe, then ſaies <hi>John, I ſaw war in Heaven, Michael and his angels fought againſt the Dragon, and the Dragon fought &amp; his angels</hi> (and whats all this to me?) truely <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> me thinks this warre in Heaven is a ſure ſymptom of the day of Judgement, the end of this world in us, when God hath by his owne power brought forth this man <hi>Jeſus</hi> in us, and hath given him power to rule and raigne in this woman, or weake paſſive <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> the Soule preſently upon the birth or bringing forth of <hi>Jeſus</hi> in it, is imediatly in a wilderneſſe, or loſt in it ſelfe, and lyes as one amazed at this ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den worke of the Lord; and in this bewildred condition of the creature, Sathan he gages warre upon it, ſhoots his fiery darts at it, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues the woman with <hi>Herod,</hi> and ſeekes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure both <hi>Chriſt</hi> with the <hi>chriſtian</hi> alſo, now therefore <hi>chriſtian,</hi> know that thy Soul is this Heaven, where this great battel is fought; thou being in a loſt bewildred eſtate, as not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which way to eſcape the woundings of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and the fiery darts of the wicked, but ſtandeſt as a ſenceleſſe lifeleſſe marke for thy <hi>ſpirituall</hi> enemies to ſhoot at: but <hi>Michael</hi> thy <hi>ſpirituall</hi> Prince <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> hee fights for thee againſt that Dragon, that whore, that anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, that labours to devoure thee; ſo that thou art that poor paſſive that lyes ſtone ſtill
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:107173:29"/>whileſt the Serpent ſtings thee, and the Dragon exerciſes his cruelty upon thee, till at laſt this <hi>Michael</hi> our Prince <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> hath by his own power and ſtrength, caſt out and ſo routed this Dragon this old Serpent, verſ. 9. That now his place is no more found in Heaven or in thy ſoul; and thus maieſt thou ſee <hi>Chriſt</hi> Judging the Whore, this Serpent in thee, inſomuch, that now this loud voyce is uttered from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or the Soul of a Saint, as in verſ. 10. <hi>Now is come ſalvation, and ſtrength, and the kingdome of our God, and the power of his Chriſt:</hi> whereas before, nothing but the dreadfull voyce of hel, wrath, anger, fury, and judgement, nothing but warrs and rumours of warrs heard in thy ſoul: yet now the day is come, <hi>Chriſt</hi> is come to Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in us, and hath condemned the whore in us, now the voyce of ſalvation is heard in thee, whereas before thou apprehendeſt God, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> did ſometimes to have ſhot the arrowes of his wrath at thee, and to have battered thy ſoul in peeces, by the thundering Cannon of his wrath; yet now thou ſeeſt there is a ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe tumults in thee, and thou now ſeeſt that ſweet meſſenger of God the eternall Spirit, drawing neere towards thee with its white Flagge of peace, joy, comfort, and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bringing comfort unto thee, by telling thee thy warfare is accompliſhed, thy iniquity
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:107173:30"/>is pardoned, and thon haſt received double at the Lords hands for all thy ſins, (and then further) now ſtrength is come alſo, which is another part of the voyce from Heaven, alas how feeble and how weake, faint, and unable was the Soul before the <hi>ſpiritual reſurrection</hi> of it? for the birth of this Child Jeſus in it, is the regeneration, or new birth of a Chriſtian: the wilderneſſe the woman fled into, is that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified dead loſt eſtate of a Chriſtian: the Grave where the Soul is buried to every living acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and the overcomming or conquering of the Dragon, or the ſpirituall ſerpent, the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the fleſh; is the reſurrection of a Saint, or that ſpirituall day of Judgement of the whore in us: Now as Jeſus raiſed up himſelfe by the power of the Father from out of the bowels of the earth, ſo by the ſtrength and power of this Jeſus, who is the reſurrection and the life, a Chriſtian riſes out of this dead condition; and ſo her mortall putting on im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, and corruption putting on incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, here is death ſwallowed up in victory. The Chriſtian now as he hath formerly been planted with Chriſt in the likeneſſe of his death; ſo likewiſe now, in the likeneſſe of his reſurrection: it bears now no longer the image of the firſt dead <hi>Adam,</hi> but is riſen in the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt, out of earth and fleſh, which
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:107173:30"/>formerly he was involved and buryed in, and by his riſing againe, overcomes the Dragon by the blood of the Lamb, kills the great Goliah, the wiſdome of the fleſh, and this is all by the ſtrength of that Strong man <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> who is entred into his temple, or the heart of man, and ſilences all theſe earthly rumors and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions in him; and ſo is the ſecond part of the voyce from Heaven fulfilled, <hi>Now is come not only ſalvation but ſtrength.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then Thirdly, <hi>The Kingdome of</hi> God that's come alſo, <hi>and the power of his Chriſt:</hi> our <hi>Saviour</hi> taught his <hi>Diſciples</hi> whil'ſt hee was in the fleſh, and knew him only after the fleſh, I ſay, he taught them <hi>to pray, thy Kingdome come;</hi> ſo that <hi>the Kingdome of Chriſt,</hi> in that ſence, was not yet come to the Diſciples; even ſo it is with every poore Chriſtian that hath attained to no more knowledge, then the fleſh of <hi>Chriſt</hi> can teach them; that do not know Chriſt any other waies, then by the beholding of his fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubſtance; as Chriſtians doe in all outward and fleſhly ordinances; that ſee no more, nor know no more of Chriſt, then Bread, Water, and Wine, and outward formes and order can teach them; the Kingdome of God is not come to them yet: while the <hi>Woman</hi> was <hi>in the Wilderneſſe,</hi> the Kingdome of God was not come in her; but when She, by the ſtrength of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:107173:31"/>God was Riſen, and had <hi>overcome by the bloud of the Lambe;</hi> then <hi>She cryed,</hi> now <hi>the Kingdome of God is come: the Woman was fed in the wilderneſse, ver.</hi> 6. in our low and loſt eſtate, God he feeds us with <hi>milke;</hi> becauſe <hi>the Kingdome of God,</hi> Chriſt in the meaſure of the Spirit is not yet come to inable us to beare ſtronger <hi>meates,</hi> in the <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe,</hi> or weake condition of Saints, <hi>God feeds them with manna;</hi> but when he brings them into <hi>Canaan</hi> he then compaſſeth them about with <hi>the flowings of Milke and Honie:</hi> this <hi>Canaan,</hi> is Chriſt, the true <hi>Reſt</hi> of a Chriſtian; the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Father</hi> in the Saints; who drawes up the Soul from theſe low diſpenſations, by degrees as it were, till he hath ſeated it in himſelf; brings the Soul out of the fleſhly knowledge of himſelf, into <hi>ſpirituall</hi> diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes of his Excellency: ſo that now the Soule prayes no more in the imbecillity of the fleſh, <hi>thy Kingdome come:</hi> ſeekes no longer in fleſhly Formes and Ordinances for <hi>the kingdome;</hi> for it is already in them, and they live in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of it: <hi>Now is come Salvation, and ſtrength and the Kingdome of God, and the power of his Chriſt:</hi> the <hi>Dragon</hi> and his <hi>Angels,</hi> they fought to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh their Kingdome in the Soul; but <hi>the Lambe hath overcome them,</hi> and ſet up his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the Chriſtian; <hi>And the Kings of the earth,</hi> as namely, the powers of the creature bring all
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:107173:31"/>their <hi>glory and Honour unto it:</hi> thus you ſee that the <hi>whore</hi> ſhall bee deſtroyed, in the <hi>laſt day,</hi> at the Second coming of Chriſt in us; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, I have diſcovered unto you one <hi>Signe</hi> of the <hi>laſt day,</hi> or day of <hi>Spirituall Judgement;</hi> which is, thoſe Combates, Warres and Commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are in a Chriſtian: I will but inſtance two particulars more, and ſo ſhall draw to a concluſion.</p>
            <p>Therefore, Secondly, a ſecond <hi>ſigne</hi> or ſymptome of the <hi>laſt day, is the Deſolution of the World;</hi> how that <hi>the Earth, and all that is therein, ſhall be burnt up; the Sonne turned into darkneſſe, the Moone into bloud; the Starres ſhall fall from Heaven:</hi> and thus God will <hi>ſhake the Heavens and the Earth; and mens hearts ſhall faile them for feare;</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the end of ſuch ſorrowfull beginings: Even thus it is with, and in a Chriſtian, at the aproaching of the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of Chriſt in him; the World begins to be diſſolved: the World is ſayd <hi>ver.</hi> 3. <hi>to bee placed in mans heart;</hi> which World in mans heart, ſhall be diſſolved by the Fire of the Spirit of Chriſt; the Heavens and the Earth, are <hi>Myſtically</hi> in man; and the Waters, with their Ebings and Flowings, are to be ſeene in the <hi>Myſterie,</hi> in man; her's God <hi>deviding the Light from the Darkneſſe,</hi> to be ſeen in man; the <hi>waters below, from the waters above the Firmament:</hi> all this is fullfilled Myſteriouſly in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:107173:32"/>man; in whom God ſeparates himſelf, who is <hi>pure and light,</hi> from the darkneſſe and nothing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the creature: The <hi>Fouls of the Ayre, and Fiſhes of the Sea,</hi> are Myſtically in man; as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thoſe flying Phantaſies, and ſwimming No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the creature; in a word, her's every thing <hi>bringing forth Fruite after its Kind</hi> in man; And all Gods creation, good in its own kind, in this <hi>firſt</hi> World, which is in mans heart.</p>
            <p>But now this firſt World, this <hi>firſt Creation</hi> muſt be diſſolved; what ever excellency God hath endued man with all, in this <hi>firſt creation;</hi> what ever maturity of Wit and ingenuity, the Lord hath lent man; how high ſo ever, and how large ſo ever, the Lord hath Naturallized the creature; yet all this excellency ſhall vaniſh away; all this worldly glory, as I ſo call it, ſhall be coſumed and burnt up: but alas! how hardly is this believed! how impoſſible is this to carnall man, that all this goodly creation and worke of God in his nature, ſhould bee anihilated; that Reaſon, Naturall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and wiſdome; nay, Nature it ſelfe, ſhould be conſumed: but this is the Lords act, <hi>his ſtrange act,</hi> his work, and <hi>wonderous worke,</hi> in a Chriſtian:</p>
            <p>Now therefore, conſider Chriſtian, that this is but the old World, or firſt, or loweſt manifeſtation of God in thee; which old <hi>world</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:107173:32"/>muſt paſs away and bee no more: <hi>John</hi> tels us that he ſaw <hi>a new Heaven and a new Earth, Rev.</hi> 21.1. <hi>for the firſt Heaven and the firſt Earth was paſſed away, and there was no more Sea;</hi> what's all this? Truly Chriſtian, in me its thus much, when this <hi>day dawnes, and this day Star, Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ariſeth in our hearts;</hi> when the morning <hi>Sun,</hi> even <hi>Jeſus</hi> breakes forth upon us in his Glory, Warmth and Splendor; then begins this <hi>world</hi> within us to be diſſolved; <hi>the Heavens and the Earth</hi> in us, begins to melt with the fervent heate of this <hi>Sun,</hi> and fall away to nothing: and the Lord inſtead of theſe frames, a <hi>new Heaven and a new Earth:</hi> So that, all that was Nature and pure Reaſon, and Ingenuity, is quite diſſolved; and a new worke wrought in the Soul; that takes up the heart above its former excellency and glory; although that were good in its kind, yet God will pleaſe, by the more glorious diſcoveries of himſelf, to drowne all this former Creation; and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get all things new in the Creature: and then not only the Heaven and the Earth paſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, but alſo <hi>there was no more Sea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Sea, or theſe Waters in man, are thoſe great overflowings, and inundations of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; the ſwellings and roarings of <hi>proud ſelfe and creature;</hi> this deep ſilence ſhall be dried up, by the heat of the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſſe:</hi> Theſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:107173:33"/>Waters are the <hi>very Throne of the Whore,</hi> or the very <hi>Seate</hi> of the wiſdome of the fleſh; now when this <hi>Sea</hi> ſhall be dried up, then there ſhall be a place no longer for this <hi>Spirituall Whore</hi> found in Heaven, nor yet in the Soul of a Saint.</p>
            <p>Oh, what cauſe of Joy is here for all the Saints, yea, what eager pantings after the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Kingdome of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſhould this beget and operate in us, to conſider, that in the day of <hi>Chriſt</hi> the whore ſhall be deſtroyed in us, the Sea ſhall be dryed up, and the Heavens and the earth ſhall paſſe away.</p>
            <p>If any man yet ſhall aske when this laſt day ſhall come, and the end of the world ſhall be accompliſhed? I anſwer then with <hi>Chriſt, That this generation ſhall not paſſe away, till all theſe things be fulfilled,</hi> all theſe things thou muſt expect to be fulfilled in thee, even in this life, O thou <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> although happily not in the fulneſſe and glory as ſhall be hereafter.</p>
            <p>Tell me therefore, O thou experienced Saint! whoſe conſcience can teſtifie all theſe things to be true: how hath the appearance of Chriſt in thee, many a time, confounded as it were all thy naturall vigour and power? how hath it ſpoyled Principalities and powers, the might and dominion of all naturall excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? how haſt thou ſeen thy ſelfe out of thy ſelfe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:107173:33"/>as it were, beyond and above that earth thou haſt been in formerly; wrapped up with <hi>Paul,</hi> in the third Heavens as it were, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding that Glory, that all thy old crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted light could never diſcerne; living for a time in <hi>that peace of God which paſſeth all underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing!</hi> Nay ſhall I yet further tell you, at the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond comming of Chriſt in us, <hi>our Sun ſhall be turned into darkneſſe, and our Moone into blood, our Stars ſhall fall from their Centre;</hi> All that light of reaſon and nature; all thoſe fleſhly meteors; as alſo fixed Stars, which have appeared at their ſeverall ſeaſons in man, which did diſcover ſomething of God to him; in a word, all the inferiour, with the ſuperiour diſcernings of God, that the creature hath had formerly, ſhal be extinguiſhed, and ſhall appeare to him to be but darkneſſe and obſcurity: the Sun or the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative light, <hi>ſhall be turned into darkneſſe, and the Moone,</hi> or that light which guides the more obſcure part of man, <hi>ſhall be turned into blood, and confuſion;</hi> and God will now create a new world in us; <hi>old things ſhall paſſe away, and all things ſhall become new in us:</hi> when the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> had been trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the diſſolution of the world, in the 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3, <hi>chap.</hi> he comes to mind the Saints of the myſterie of that hiſtory, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>Nevertheleſſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we, according to his promiſe, looke for new Heavens and new earth, wherein dwelleth righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, although this old foundation and Fabrick ſhall
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:107173:34"/>be diſſolved, and</hi> Chriſt, <hi>that day of the Lord, ſhall come even as a thiefe in the night, and deprive us of all the excellency of our preſent ſtation; waſte, deſtroy, and burne up all our Gold, Silver, and precious ſtones, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume all the Glory of our preſent being,</hi> yet ſayes hee here is one comfort, <hi>wee looke for a new Heaven and a new earth, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſſe,</hi> God never confounds the old, but he brings a new, the manner of Gods new creation is, to new modelize the heart, to new mould the creature, to create a new Chriſtian, as it were to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuallize the Chriſtian; in a word, it is to ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low up the ſoul in himſelfe, to drown, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found, and bring to an end, all creature glory, in his own incomprehenſive excellency.</p>
            <p>So that the Saints are ſaid to bee that new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that came down from God, deck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and adorn'd with the Glory of God only, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Bride adorned for her husband:</p>
            <p>They are called new, becauſe Chriſt in them hath created a new world; this new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had no temple in it of it ſelfe, but the Lord God and the Lamb were the temple of it; truly that ſoul in whom the Lord God hath mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this deſolation of creature excellency, and hath created all things a new; this new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> or new <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> hath no temple but <hi>Chriſt.</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> typicall Jeruſalem there was a temple, but Chriſt propheſied, <hi>That there ſhould not be one ſton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:107173:34"/>left upon another, that ſhould not be throwne downe, Matth.</hi> 24. Even ſo when God creates all things new in a Chriſtian, he will demolliſh all that was in his ſtead, before he came to eſtabliſh his new creation; and he will make himſelfe the temple of a Chriſtian: what ever the ſoul ſees in any outward things, as Formes, Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Worſhips and the like, yet Chriſt will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy and throw downe, and bring to nought theſe things, and make himſelfe all this, and much more to the Chriſtian: and thus you may ſee the day of Judgement in a Chriſtian: here you may ſee Chriſt ſending his ſpirit into the worldly heart of man, convincing it of Judgement, becauſe the prince of this world is judged in him.</p>
            <p>I proceed now, to the third diſcovery of the laſt day, which is, namely, <hi>The diſtruction of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, or the downfall of the whore;</hi> which doth yet further manifeſt to us, that this laſt day is in us; the comming of this day of Jeſus; and the appearance of this Star in us, is the laſt day of the whore in us: no ſooner doth Chriſt appear, but downe falls the Kingdome of the ſerpent, our fleſhly wiſdome; and therefore if thou wouldſt know how this Antichriſt ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, the Apoſtle tells us, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2, 8. <hi>That the Lord ſhal conſume him with the breath of his mouth, and the brightneſſe of his comming;</hi> This bright
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:107173:35"/>comming of Chriſt in us, ſhall diſpell that darkneſs, &amp; diſcover that fogge that with-hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth or hinders the revelation of the whore; Chriſt will then put aſide this veile which is before this varlets face, namely, all her ſpecious pretences, and ſhewes of glory. Chriſt is that mountaine ſpoken of in the 25. <hi>Iſa. In whom God ſhall deſtroy the veile of the covering that is caſt over all people:</hi> but this muſt be fulfilled, when this mountaine Chriſt Jeſus, ſhall be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed upon the top of the mountaines in our ſouls; or when Chriſt by his owne power hath ſeated himſelf in us, above every high thought, and vaine imagination; when the child Jeſus is given to us, and hath gotten the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon his ſhoulders; this is the time of the whores demolition in us; I ſay it is the worke of Chriſt by his comming in a Saint, to diſcover the Whore to him, to take away that veil of fleſh, and thoſe miſts of obſurity, which this harlot hath interpoſed between her ſelfe and the ſoul: when the day dawnes, the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vaniſheth away; even ſo, when this day, Chriſt Jeſus dawn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in thy heart; when day breaks, as I may ſo ſay, in thy ſoul, then begins the darkneſſe in thy heart to flee away; and now thou commeſt to be one of the Children of the day. In a word, now thou canſt ſee, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, and diſtinguiſh, and before thou couldeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:107173:35"/>not: alas ſirs! a poore ſoul that walks in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſees by no other light but by the blaze of ſelfe, and by the ſparks of his own fire; he may be compared to a man that ſees by can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle light, who cannot diſcerne one colour from another: even ſo it is with all naturall men, they are not able to ſee whats good from evill, or whats light from darkneſſe: O the palpable blindneſſe of all poore creatures, in whom this day, Chriſt does not appeare! this, it is to have eyes and ſee not, eares and heare not.</p>
            <p>This ſad obſcurity of a man that walkes not in the light, may fitly be compared to that darkneſſe which might be felt; the ſoul feeles many times, what his blindneſſe is, how it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives him of the beatificall viſion of God; brings him to wander from the way, Chriſt Jeſus cauſes him many times to ſtumble at that ſtumbling ſtone; and all this is becauſe the day is not dawned as yet: but now, when the Sun of righteouſneſſe ariſes in the Soul, why then, here comes light to them that ſit in darkneſſe and in the ſhadow of death, and now this light guides the ſoul into the way of peace: It is ſaid of new Jeruſalem, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. <hi>That it needed not the light of the Sun, or of the Moone, for the glory of God did lighten it, and the Lamb was the light thereof;</hi> all which in me is thus much, when God comes
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:107173:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>to create a new Heaven and a new earth in a Chriſtian, when he comes by the power of that regenerating ſpirit, to make his Jeruſalem a new Jeruſalem; in this new eſtate, he will give her new light to walke by, ſo that now the Saints ſhall have no need of the old Sun, or the old Moone; no need of the old light of reaſon and nature, but her's new light brought forth now in the ſoul; the new light is Chriſt, or the Lamb, who by the radiant beames of his ſplendor, fills the ſoul with the glory of the Father, and deſtroyes, or diſtinguiſhes all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inferiour lights in the ſoul. We live in a generation, wherein both Preſſe, and Pulpit, doth cry down new lights; and truely I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not much blame them that ſo doe, becauſe as yet they walke in the light of the old Sun and Moone, and are to be comprehended, under the notion of old Jeruſalem; but tell me now? when the Spirit of Glory hath darkned this Sun, and turned this Moone into blood; quite confounded &amp; brought to nothing, the higheſt ſphere of this naturall excellency in them, when this old Jeruſalem comes to bee made new? then you ſhall heare a new voyce, crying up the new light of God manifeſted in them; O Chriſtian; I tell thee thou art a thrice hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py man, whom the Lord hath made the Lamb a light unto thee; this Lamb light, is an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:107173:36"/>light, a righteous light, a pure light, a diſcovering light; it is this light that diſcovers the hidden and obſcure whore, unto thee; it is the light of Chriſt that uncovers, and ſtrips the whore ſtarke naked before thee, of all her glory and excellency; ſo that now thou behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt her out of her purple and ſcarlet colour, even in her very nakedneſſe and ſhame: And thus you ſee how Chriſt in his day, in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, does firſt of all diſcover the whore to him.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, in this laſt day or Sun riſing of Chriſt in a Chriſtian, it is the worke of Chriſt to deſtroy, as well as to diſcover this whore in us, as it is the property of light to deſtroy darkneſſe; ſo it is the property of Chriſt to deſtroy antichriſt in the day of his appearance: it will be the worke of Chriſt by his comming in thee, to roote out that ſpirit of antichriſt, head and tayle, root and branch; inſomuch that there ſhall not be left one hoof of the beaſt in thee: when <hi>John</hi> ſaw the Angell come downe from heaven endued with great power, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.1. <hi>Who inlightned the earth with his glory, immediatly he heard this voyce, Babylon is fallen, is fallen, and is become the habitation of divels, the hould of every foule ſpirit, and a cage of every un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane and hatefull bird;</hi> all which teacheth me thus much, that when that Angell of the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:107173:37"/>laſting covenant Chriſt Jeſus, is by the Father ſent down into the hearts of his Saints, who comes by the power of his Spirit, and enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens the earth or earthly man with his glory: when the earth is filled with the knowledge of the Lord; when the glory of this Sun comes to enlighten and beautifie our earthy hearts; then is the time of Babylons downfall; now is the ſeaſon of the whores deſtruction; now is the Saints time of <hi>Halelujah;</hi> now rejoyce over her thou Heaven, and all the holy Apoſtles and Prophets, for God hath avenged you on her: <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. The Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> tells us, <hi>chap.</hi> 4. <hi>That the day comes that ſhall burne as an Oven;</hi> this day is Chriſt Jeſus, who indeed ſhall ſo baptize us with the holy Ghoſt, and Fire, as that he ſhall conſume and burne up, waſte, and deſtroy all the appearances of the Whore, the wiſdome of the fleſh, and therefore the ſame prophet tells us, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.34. <hi>That he ſhall ſit as a Refiners fire, and as Fullers Soape, and he ſhall purifie the Sons of Levi, that they may offer to the Lord, an offering in righteouſneſſe;</hi> this day muſt burne in us; this Jeſus muſt be a refiners fire to us, before we ſhal ſee the downefall of myſticall Babylon: the worke that Chriſt hath to doe in us, is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy mortallity, and to cloath us with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, to deſtroy this corruption, and to cloath us with the incorruptible righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of himſelfe.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:107173:37"/>
            <p>After the downfall of the whore, <hi>Revel.</hi> 19. <hi>John</hi> tells us, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>That there was granted to the Lambs wife, that ſhe ſhould be arrayed in fine linnen, cleare and white, &amp;c.</hi> In which I obſerve, firſt, the love of Chriſt to the Soul; Chriſt did firſt of all by his blood and paſſion, purchaſe the Soul to himſelfe, to the end that ſhe ſhould be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Spouſe unto him; but ſhe hath adulterized from her husband; committed harlotry from her firſt lover; and hath taken part with anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt againſt him: upon which adultery, the jealouſie of the Lord ariſes in himſelfe, and as jealouſie is ſaid to be the rage of a man, ſo the Lord (as I may ſay) in the rage of this jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, comes, and deſtroyes this antichriſt, kils ſin in the Chriſtian; ſheaths the ſword of the ſpirit in the bowels of this ſpiritual antichriſt; breakes the head of this ſerpent in us: but yet notwithſtanding, entertaines this adulterized creature into his love and favour; does yet once more eſpouſe her to himſelfe, by a freſh act and manifeſtation of love and favour: you may ſee an embleme of this love in <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 3.1 where God commands the Prophet to go with a meſſage of love, to the woman that had play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the harlot with him; <hi>Goe, yet love a woman be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of her friend, yet an adultreſſe: though ſhe an adultreſſe, yet I am her friend; though ſhe an harlot, yet I ſend love greetings towards her: though ſhe hath been
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:107173:38"/>unconſtant towards me, yet I will owne her to be my wife, my Spouſe, my beloved;</hi> and therefore the text ſaies, that it was granted to the Lambs wife, that ſhee ſhould bee arrayed in linnen, clean &amp; white: which likewiſe dictates to me,</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the Second place, the purity that this <hi>day of burning,</hi> Chriſt Jeſus in Spirit, works in the heart of his People; he doth not only take from it the <hi>garment ſpotted with the fleſh,</hi> but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, Cloathes it with the <hi>ſhinning Robe of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe;</hi> he doth not only empty a Soul of its owne corruption; but likewiſe fills it with his glory: beautifies it with his own adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: O Faire, beautifull, amiable creature! whoſe beauty and excellency conſiſts in Chriſt that divine centre of bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>htneſſe and glory: this will ſend a Saint to the depth of admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; behold! <hi>what manner of love hath the Father beſtowed upon us, that we ſhould be called the Sons of God?</hi> that God ſhould thus by the power of the Spirit, conſume all this droſs and coruption in us; and bring us by that divine light to ſee our <hi>vnion with the Father, in the Son;</hi> and to ſee the glory of our <hi>Adoption</hi> in <hi>Jeſus;</hi> and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold our ſelves in the fleſh of our <hi>elder Brother,</hi> at the <hi>Right-hand of the Father?</hi> this is mercy <hi>paſt</hi> diſcerning, and worth admiration!</p>
            <p>Thus will God in the power of his Spirit, Judge this <hi>ſpirituall Whore</hi> in us; and eaſe us of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:107173:38"/>the vaſſallage, and ſervitude we were in to our owne ſelves: thus ſhall the <hi>brats of this ſpirituall Babylon,</hi> the wiſdome of the fleſh, be deſtroyed by that happy man, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God ſaith, <hi>Jſa.</hi> 17.12. concerning this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Babylon, <hi>That hee will make a man more precious then fine Gold, or the Golden wedge of Opher;</hi> this man is Chriſt, who <hi>in the day of his power,</hi> and in the confounding of this Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Babell in us, ſhall be made unto us, more precious then the higheſt creature excellency: never till now, will the Saints come to value and to prize Chriſt, till they ſee what he doth in them.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>how beautifull upon the mountains, are the feete of them that bring glad tidings of good things; that publiſheth Salvation; that ſaith unto Zion, thy God raineth?</hi> Thy Meſſenger upon the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, is Chriſt Jeſus; who comes <hi>Leaping over the mountaines, and skiping over the hils</hi> of difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; that lies in the way, and appeares in glory to his <hi>Spouſe</hi> or beloved Chriſtian, and declares the meſſage of glad tidings to him; Namely, <hi>That his warfare is accompliſhed, that his iniquity is pardoned;</hi> the battell between <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> and the <hi>Lamb</hi> is finiſhed; and the <hi>Lamb</hi> or inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>Spirit,</hi> hath over-come all by his power and ſtrength; and now likewiſe he declares to <hi>Zion</hi> or the ſoul of a <hi>Saint, that his God raineth;
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:107173:39"/>now is come the Kingdome of our God, &amp; the power of his Chriſt; therfore Halelujah; for Babylon is fallen, the Whore</hi> is deſtroyed; <hi>God hath now put into the hearts of the Kings of the Earth</hi> (or powers of earthly man) <hi>to hate the whore, and reward her as ſhe hath rewarded them;</hi> and therefore again, <hi>Halelujah, for the Lord God omnipotent raigneth, and the Kingdomes of the whore are become the Kingdomes of the Lord and of his Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All that remaines behind therefore, is but one word of application, which ſhall be but only my exhortation to al poor ſouls that are groaning under this burdenſome task and <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian bondage</hi> of the Whore: doubtleſſe their are many to whom theſe my poor endeavours may offer themſelves; whoſe portion it is to groane under this ſpirituall vaſſallage, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour under this <hi>bodyof death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh Chriſtian! whatever thy condition bee, caſt not away thy confidence; but waite upon the Lord, and thou ſhalt <hi>renew thy ſtrength;</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the returne, or <hi>Second coming of Chriſt</hi> in thee; pray dayly, that Chriſts <hi>Kingdome</hi> may come in thee; that the Lord would eſtabliſh his own Throne in thy heart; expect the comming of the <hi>Meſſenger of the Covenant</hi> into his <hi>Temple,</hi> or thy heart; even the Lord Chriſt; whom thou <hi>ſeekeſt:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh! Labour to ſee that Chriſt is approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:107173:39"/>neare thee, though the <hi>cloudes</hi> of ſinne and wickedneſſe hinder the ſight of him; know al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that this <hi>ſpirituall Sonne,</hi> Chriſt Jeſus will breake away the clouds; will diſpell the miſts of iniquity in thee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; and will <hi>breake out</hi> upon thee, in his full warmth and ſplendor; and will bring thee to walke in the light of his glory.</p>
            <p>It was ſaid of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that hee <hi>ſaw the day of Chriſt, and was glad;</hi> how gladly then ſhould the Saints expect, and <hi>ſpiritually</hi> ſee this day to bee at hand in them; In which they ſhall be freed from that burthen which they now undergoe? Shall I tell thee yet farther, for thy comfort <hi>O</hi> Chriſtian! this <hi>Jeſus</hi> that comes, <hi>will come, and will not tarry:</hi> The Lord ſees thee in thy poore weake condition; he takes notice of thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny foiles that thy wicked heart gives thee; hee heares thy ſighings, cryes, and groanes; hee yearns after thee; he makes haſte to come unto thee ſo quickly, as may conduce to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of his glory, and thy Souls further peace and comfort.</p>
            <p>Thus in brief, I have diſcovered to you, in ſome meaſure, <hi>the Myſterie of iniquity</hi> which workes in all of us; the <hi>great Whore; the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Babylon, with her Riſe, and her Down-fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which poore Treatiſe, I deſire that thoſe to whom it ſhall come, would thus underſtand
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:107173:40"/>me; that I doe not in any wiſe ſeeke hereby to ſet up my owne opinion, as <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove others; but doe only declare what I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from good Reaſon, to bee the manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative minde of God unto me: And in all my Myſticall applying of any Scriptures; I would not be thought hereby to endeavour the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> but only ſo much of the Hiſtory, as I ſee verified in me, in the <hi>Myſterie:</hi> I have preſumed in my preſent light, to declare to all men: what is of God, in my weake en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, I deſire him to make knowne; by the declarative power of his <hi>ſpirit:</hi> what is of ſelf, I deſire to have a heart to diſclaime it, when the Lord ſhall manifeſt it unto me; and ſo I commit my Labour to him, from whence only, I expect a reward: deſiring nothing from any man, but a favourable conſtruction of that which I have declared to all men, in the bowels of love and affection.</p>
            <p>For my own part, I am one that waiteth for the Kingdome and power of Chriſt, to bee manifeſted in me: I deſire to ſee farther the glorious dawnings of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and riſings of his glory in mee; and <hi>looking for, and haſting to the comming of the day of Jeſus;</hi> in which, <hi>all old things ſhall paſſe away, and all things ſhall become new</hi>
            </p>
            <p>and that which I conceive in this condition is the beſt courſe for my ſelfe to take, I ſhall
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:107173:40"/>likewiſe faſten the ſame advice upon all others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who is amongſt you that feareth the Lord, that obeyeth the voyce of his Servant, that walketh in darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſeeth no light, let him truſt in the name of the Lord, and ſtay himſelfe upon his God.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Decemb. 12. 1647.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Joſ. Salmon.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
